<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->
<sect1 xml:id="install.macosx.bundled" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
 <title>Using the bundled PHP prior to macOS Monterey</title>
 <simpara>
  PHP is bundled with macOS since macOS X (10.0.0) prior to macOS Monterey (12.0.0).
  Enabling PHP with the default web server requires uncommenting a few lines in the 
  Apache configuration file <filename>httpd.conf</filename> whereas the
  <acronym>CGI</acronym> and/or <acronym>CLI</acronym> are enabled by
  default (easily accessible via the Terminal program).
 </simpara>
 <simpara>
  Enabling PHP using the instructions below is meant for quickly setting up
  a local development environment.  It's <emphasis>highly recommended</emphasis>
  to always upgrade PHP to the newest version. Like most live software,
  newer versions are created to fix bugs and add features and PHP being is
  no different.  See the appropriate macOS installation documentation for
  further details. The following instructions are geared towards a beginner
  with details provided for getting a default setup to work. All users are
  encouraged to compile, or install a new packaged version.
 </simpara>
 <simpara>
  The standard installation type is using mod_php, and enabling the bundled
  mod_php on macOS for the Apache web server (the default web server,
  that is accessible via System Preferences) involves the following steps:
 </simpara>
 <para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
     Locate and open the Apache configuration file. By default, the location
     is as follows: <filename>/private/etc/apache2/httpd.conf</filename>
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
     Using <literal>Finder</literal> or <literal>Spotlight</literal> to find
     this file may prove difficult as by default it's private and owned by
     the <literal>root</literal> user.
    </simpara>
    <note>
     <simpara>
      One way to open this is by using a Unix based text editor in the
      Terminal, for example <literal>nano</literal>, and because the
      file is owned by <literal>root</literal> we'll use the <literal>sudo</literal> command
      to open it (as <literal>root</literal>) so for example type the following into the
      <literal>Terminal</literal> Application (after, it will prompt for
      a password):
      <literal>sudo nano /private/etc/apache2/httpd.conf</literal>
     </simpara>
     <simpara>
      Noteworthy nano commands: <literal>^w</literal> (search),
      <literal>^o</literal> (save), and <literal>^x</literal> (exit) where
      <literal>^</literal> represents the Ctrl key.
     </simpara>
    </note>
    <note>
     <simpara>
      Versions of Mac OS X prior to 10.5 were bundled with older versions of
      PHP and Apache.  As such, the Apache configuration file on legacy
      machines may be <filename>/etc/httpd/httpd.conf</filename>.
     </simpara>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     With a text editor, uncomment the lines (by removing the #) that look
     similar to the following (these two lines are often not together,
     locate them both in the file):
     <screen>
<![CDATA[
# LoadModule php5_module libexec/httpd/libphp5.so

# AddModule mod_php5.c
]]>
     </screen>
      Notice the location/path. When building PHP in the future, the above
      files should be replaced or commented out.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Be sure the desired extensions will parse as PHP (examples:
     <filename class="extension">.php</filename>, <filename class="extension">.html</filename>
     and <filename class="extension">.inc</filename>).
    </para>
    <para>
     Due to the following statement already existing in
     <filename>httpd.conf</filename> (as of Mac Panther), once PHP is
     enabled the <filename class="extension">.php</filename> files will automatically
     parse as PHP.
     <screen>
<![CDATA[
<IfModule mod_php5.c>
    # If php is turned on, we respect .php and .phps files.
    AddType application/x-httpd-php .php
    AddType application/x-httpd-php-source .phps

    # Since most users will want index.php to work we
    # also automatically enable index.php
    <IfModule mod_dir.c>
        DirectoryIndex index.html index.php
    </IfModule>
</IfModule>
]]>
     </screen>
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      Before Mac OS X 10.5 (Leopard), PHP 4 was bundled instead of PHP 5 in
      which case the above instructions will differ slightly by changing
      5's to 4's.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
     Be sure the DirectoryIndex loads the desired default index file
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
     This is also set in <filename>httpd.conf</filename>. Typically
     <filename>index.php</filename> and <filename>index.html</filename> are
     used. By default <filename>index.php</filename> is enabled because
     it's also in the PHP check shown above. Adjust accordingly.
    </simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
     Set the &php.ini; location or use the default
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
     A typical default location on macOS is
     <filename>/usr/local/php/php.ini</filename> and a call to
     <function>phpinfo</function> will reveal this information.
     If a &php.ini; is not used, PHP will use all default values.
     See also the related FAQ on
     <link linkend="faq.installation.phpini">finding php.ini</link>.
    </simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
     Locate or set the <literal>DocumentRoot</literal>
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
     This is the root directory for all the web files. Files in this directory
     are served from the web server so the PHP files will parse as PHP before
     outputting them to the browser. A typical default path is
     <filename>/Library/WebServer/Documents</filename> but this can be set to
     anything in <filename>httpd.conf</filename>.  Alternatively, the default
     <filename>DocumentRoot</filename> for individual users is
     <filename>/Users/yourusername/Sites</filename>
    </simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
     Create a <function>phpinfo</function> file
    </simpara>
    <para>
     The <function>phpinfo</function> function will display information about PHP.
     Consider creating a file in the DocumentRoot with the following PHP code:
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php phpinfo(); ?>
]]>
     </programlisting>
    </para> 
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
     Restart Apache, and load the PHP file created above
    </simpara>
    <para>
     To restart, either execute <literal>sudo apachectl graceful</literal> in
     the shell or stop/start the "Personal Web Server" option in the
     macOS System Preferences. By default, loading local files in the browser
     will have an <acronym>URL</acronym> like so:
     <filename>http://localhost/info.php</filename> Or using the DocumentRoot
     in the user directory is another option and would end up looking like:
     <filename>http://localhost/~yourusername/info.php</filename>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </para>
 <simpara>
  The <acronym>CLI</acronym> (or <acronym>CGI</acronym> in older versions) is
  appropriately named <filename>php</filename> and likely exists as
  <filename>/usr/bin/php</filename>. Open up the terminal, read the
  <link linkend="features.commandline">command line section</link> of the PHP
  manual, and execute <literal>php -v</literal> to check the PHP version of
  this PHP binary. A call to <function>phpinfo</function> will also reveal
  this information.
 </simpara>
</sect1>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
