<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->

<book xml:id="book.mysqlnd-ms" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Mysqlnd replication and load balancing plugin</title>
 <titleabbrev>mysqlnd_ms</titleabbrev>

 <preface xml:id="intro.mysqlnd-ms">
  &reftitle.intro;
  <para>
   The mysqlnd replication and load balancing plugin (<literal>mysqlnd_ms</literal>)
   adds easy to use MySQL replication support to all PHP MySQL extensions that use
   <link linkend="book.mysqlnd">mysqlnd</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   As of version PHP 5.3.3 the MySQL native driver for PHP 
   (<literal>mysqlnd</literal>)
   features an internal plugin C API. C plugins, such as the replication and
   load balancing plugin, can extend the functionality of
   <link linkend="book.mysqlnd">mysqlnd</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The MySQL native driver for PHP is a C library which ships together with
   PHP as of PHP 5.3.0. It serves as a drop-in replacement for the
   MySQL Client Library (AKA libmysql/libmysqlclient). Using mysqlnd has
   several advantages: no extra downloads because it comes with PHP,
   PHP license, lower memory consumption in certain cases,
   new functionality such as asynchronous queries.
  </para>
  <para>
   Mysqlnd plugins such as the replication and load balancing plugin operate
   mostly transparent from an user perspective. The replication and load balancing
   plugin supports all PHP applications
   and all PHP MySQL extensions (
   <link linkend="ref.mysqli">mysqli</link>,
   <link linkend="ref.mysql">mysql</link>,
   <link linkend="ref.pdo-mysql">PDO_MYSQL</link>).
   It does not change existing APIs. Therefore, it can easily be used with
   existing PHP applications.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    The mysqlnd replication and load balancing plugin is in alpha status.
    It is not feature complete.
   </para>
  </note>
  <section xml:id="mysqlnd-ms.key_features">
   <title>Key Features</title>
   <para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Transparent and therefore easy to use
      </para>
      <para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          supports all PHP MySQL extensions
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          no API changes
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          very little, if any, application changes required, dependent on the usage scenario required
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Featured read-write split strategies
      </para>
      <para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Automatic detection of SELECT, supports SQL hints to overrule automatism
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          user-defined
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Featured load balancing strategies
      </para>
      <para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Round Robin: choose different slave in round robin fashion for every slave request.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Random: choose random slave for every slave request.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Random once (sticky): choose random slave once to run all slave requests for the duration of a web request.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          User-defined. The application can register callbacks with mysqlnd_ms.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="mysqlnd-ms.limitations">
   <title>Limitations</title>
   <para>
    The plugin does not support MySQL replication setups with more
    than one master server.
   </para>
   <para>
    The built-in read/write-split mechanism is very basic. Every
    query which starts with <literal>SELECT</literal>
    is considered a read request to be sent to a MySQL slave server.
    All other queries, including, for example, <literal>SHOW</literal>
    statements, are considered as write requests to be sent to the MySQL master server.
    The build-in behaviour can be overruled using 
    <link linkend="mysqlnd-ms.constants">SQL hints</link> or an user-defined
    <link linkend="function.mysqlnd-ms-set-user-pick-server">callback function</link>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The read/write splitter is not aware of multi-statements. Multi-statements
    are considered as one statement. The decision of where to run the statement
    will be based on the beginning of the statement string.
   </para>
   <para>
    The plugin does not support native prepared statements. Please
    note that <link linkend="ref.pdo-mysql">PDO_MySQL</link> is using a
    client-side prepared statement emulation by default. Client-side emulated
    prepared statements are fully supported by the replication and load balancing
    plugin because the emulation is not using native prepared statements.
    If you are using PHP based database abstraction, please consult the
    vendor manual to learn if a client-side prepared statement emulation is
    used.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     Application must be aware of the consequences of connection switches performed
     for load balancing purpose. Please check the documentation on 
     <link linkend="mysqlnd-ms.pooling">connection pooling and switching</link>,
     <link linkend="mysqlnd-ms.transaction">transaction handling</link>,
     <link linkend="mysqlnd-ms.failover">failover</link> 
     <link linkend="mysqlnd-ms.loadbalancing">load balancing</link> and 
     <link linkend="mysqlnd-ms.rwsplit">read-write splitting</link> carefully.
    </para>
   </note>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="mysqlnd-ms.name">
   <title>On the name</title>
   <para>
    The shortcut <literal>mysqlnd_ms</literal> 
    stands for <literal>mysqlnd master slave plugin</literal>. The name
    was choosen for a quick-and-dirty proof-of-concept. In the beginning
    the developers did not expect to continue using the code base.
   </para>
  </section>
 </preface>

 &reference.mysqlnd-ms.quickstart;
 &reference.mysqlnd-ms.concepts;
 &reference.mysqlnd-ms.setup;
 &reference.mysqlnd-ms.constants; 
 &reference.mysqlnd-ms.reference; 

</book>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
