<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.16 $ -->
 <chapter id="pear.standards">
  <title>PEAR Coding Standards</title>
  <note>
   <simpara>
    The PEAR Coding Standards applies to code that is to become a part
    of PEAR, either distributed with PHP or available for download via
    PEAR's install tool.
   </simpara>
  </note>
  <sect1 id="pear.standards.indenting">
   <title>Indenting</title>
   <para>
    Use an indent of 4 spaces, with no tabs. If you use Emacs to edit PEAR
    code, you should set indent-tabs-mode to nil. Here is an example mode
    hook that will set up Emacs according to these guidelines (you will
    need to ensure that it is called when you are editing PHP files):
    <programlisting role="elisp">
<![CDATA[
(defun php-mode-hook ()
  (setq tab-width 4
        c-basic-offset 4
        c-hanging-comment-ender-p nil
  	indent-tabs-mode
	(not
	 (and (string-match "/\\(PEAR\\|pear\\)/" (buffer-file-name))
	      (string-match "\.php$" (buffer-file-name))))))
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
   <para>Here are vim rules for the same thing:
    <programlisting role="vim">
<![CDATA[
  set expandtab 
  set shiftwidth=4 
  set tabstop=4 
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.control">
   <title>Control Structures</title>
   <para>
    These include if, for, while, switch, etc. Here is an example if
    statement, since it is the most complicated of them:
    <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
if ((condition1) || (condition2)) {
    action1;
} elseif ((condition3) && (condition4)) {
    action2;
} else {
    defaultaction;
}
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
   <simpara>
    Control statements should have one space between the control keyword
    and opening parenthesis, to distinguish them from function calls.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    You are strongly encouraged to always use curly braces even in
    situations where they are technically optional. Having them
    increases readability and decreases the likelihood of logic errors
    being introduced when new lines are added.
   </simpara>
   <para>
    For switch statements:
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
switch (condition) {
case 1:
    action1;
    break;

case 2:
    action2;
    break;

default:
    defaultaction;
    break;

}
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.funcalls">
   <title>Function Calls</title>
   <para>
    Functions should be called with no spaces between the function
    name, the opening parenthesis, and the first parameter; spaces
    between commas and each parameter, and no space between the last
    parameter, the closing parenthesis, and the semicolon. Here's an
    example:
    <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
$var = foo($bar, $baz, $quux);
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
   <para>
    As displayed above, there should be one space on either side of an
    equals sign used to assign the return value of a function to a
    variable. In the case of a block of related assignments, more space
    may be inserted to promote readability:
    <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
$short         = foo($bar);
$long_variable = foo($baz);
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.funcdef">
   <title>Function Definitions</title>
   <para>
    Function declaractions follow the "one true brace" convention:
    <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
function fooFunction($arg1, $arg2 = '')
{
    if (condition) {
        statement;
    }
    return $val;
}
]]>
</programlisting>
   </para>
   <para>
    Arguments with default values go at the end of the argument list.
    Always attempt to return a meaningful value from a function if one
    is appropriate. Here is a slightly longer example:
    <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
function connect(&$dsn, $persistent = false)
{
    if (is_array($dsn)) {
        $dsninfo = &$dsn;
    } else {
        $dsninfo = DB::parseDSN($dsn);
    }
    
    if (!$dsninfo || !$dsninfo['phptype']) {
        return $this->raiseError();
    }
    
    return true;
}
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.comments">
   <title>Comments</title>
   <para>
    Inline documentation for classes should follow the PHPDoc
    convention, similar to Javadoc. More information about PHPDoc can
    be found here: <ulink url="&url.phpdoc;">&url.phpdoc;</ulink>
   </para>
   <para>
    Non-documentation comments are strongly encouraged. A general rule of
    thumb is that if you look at a section of code and think "Wow, I don't
    want to try and describe that", you need to comment it before you
    forget how it works.
   </para>
   <para>
    C style comments (/* */) and standard C++ comments (//) are both
    fine. Use of Perl/shell style comments (#) is discouraged.
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.including">
   <title>Including Code</title>
   <para>
    Anywhere you are unconditionally including a class file, use
    <function>require_once</function>. Anywhere you are conditionally
    including a class file (for example, factory methods), use
    <function>include_once</function>. Either of these will ensure
    that class files are included only once. They share the same file
    list, so you don't need to worry about mixing them - a file
    included with <function>require_once</function> will not be
    included again by <function>include_once</function>.
    <note>
     <simpara>
      <function>include_once</function> and
      <function>require_once</function> are statements, not
      functions. You don't <emphasis>need</emphasis> parentheses
      around the filename to be included.
     </simpara>
    </note>
   </para>    
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.tags">
   <title>PHP Code Tags</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis>Always</emphasis> use <literal>&lt;?php ?></literal> to
    delimit PHP code, not the <literal>&lt;? ?></literal> shorthand.
    This is required for PEAR compliance and is also the most portable
    way to include PHP code on differing operating systems and setups.
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.header">
   <title>Header Comment Blocks</title>
   <para>
    All source code files in the core PEAR distribution should contain
    the following comment block as the header:
    <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
/* vim: set expandtab tabstop=4 shiftwidth=4: */
// +----------------------------------------------------------------------+
// | PHP version 4.0                                                      |
// +----------------------------------------------------------------------+
// | Copyright (c) 1997, 1998, 1999, 2000, 2001 The PHP Group             |
// +----------------------------------------------------------------------+
// | This source file is subject to version 2.0 of the PHP license,       |
// | that is bundled with this package in the file LICENSE, and is        |
// | available at through the world-wide-web at                           |
// | http://www.php.net/license/2_02.txt.                                 |
// | If you did not receive a copy of the PHP license and are unable to   |
// | obtain it through the world-wide-web, please send a note to          |
// | license@php.net so we can mail you a copy immediately.               |
// +----------------------------------------------------------------------+
// | Authors: Original Author <author@example.com>                        |
// |          Your Name <you@example.com>                                 |
// +----------------------------------------------------------------------+
//
// $Id: standards.xml,v 1.16 2001-12-12 20:47:43 hholzgra Exp $
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>
   <para>   
    There's no hard rule to determine when a new code contributer
    should be added to the list of authors for a given source file.
    In general, their changes should fall into the "substantial"
    category (meaning somewhere around 10% to 20% of code changes).
    Exceptions could be made for rewriting functions or contributing
    new logic.
   </para>
   <para>
    Simple code reorganization or bug fixes would not justify the
    addition of a new individual to the list of authors.
   </para>
   <para>
    Files not in the core PEAR repository should have a similar block
    stating the copyright, the license, and the authors. All files
    should include the modeline comments to encourage consistency.
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.cvs">
   <title>Using CVS</title>
   <simpara>
    This section applies only to packages using CVS at cvs.php.net.
   </simpara>
   <para>
    Include the &dollar;Id&dollar; CVS keyword in each file.  As each file
    is edited, add this tag if it's not yet present (or replace
    existing forms such as "Last Modified:", etc.).
<!--
    <note>
     <simpara>
      We have a custom $Horde tag in Horde cvs to track our versions
      seperately; we could do the same and make a $PEAR tag, that
      would remain even if PEAR files were put into another source
      control system, etc...]
     </simpara>
    </note>
-->
   </para>
   <para>
    The rest of this section assumes that you have basic knowledge
    about CVS tags and branches.
   </para>
   <para>
    CVS tags are used to label which revisions of the files in your
    package belong to a given release.  Below is a list of the
    required and suggested CVS tags:

    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>RELEASE_<replaceable>n_n</replaceable></term>
      <listitem>
       <simpara>
	(required) Used for tagging a release.  If you don't use it,
	there's no way to go back and retrieve your package from the
	CVS server in the state it was in at the time of the release.
       </simpara>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>QA_<replaceable>n_n</replaceable></term>
      <listitem>
       <simpara>
	(branch, optional) If you feel you need to roll out a
	release candidate before releasing, it's a good idea to make a
	branch for it so you can isolate the release and apply only
	those critical fixes before the actual release.  Meanwhile,
	normal development may continue on the main trunk.
       </simpara>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>MAINT_<replaceable>n_n</replaceable></term>
      <listitem>
       <simpara>
	(branch, optional) If you need to make "micro-releases" (for
	example 1.2.1 and so on after 1.2), you can use a branch for
	that too, if your main trunk is very active and you want only
	minor changes between your micro-releases.
       </simpara>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    Only the RELEASE tag is required, the rest are recommended for
    your convenience.
   </para>
   <para>
    Below is an example of how to tag the 1.2 release of the
    "Money_Fast" package:
    <informalexample>
     <screen><prompt>$ </prompt><command>cd pear/Money_Fast</command>
<prompt>$ </prompt><command>cvs tag RELEASE_1_2</command>
<computeroutput>T Fast.php
T README
T package.xml
</computeroutput>
</screen>
    </informalexample>
    By doing this you make it possible for the PEAR web site to take
    you through the rest of your release process.
   </para>
   <para>
    Here's an example of how to create a QA branch:
    <informalexample>
     <screen><prompt>$ </prompt><command>cvs tag QA_2_0_BP</command>
...
<prompt>$ </prompt><command>cvs rtag -b -r QA_2_0_BP QA_2_0</command>
<prompt>$ </prompt><command>cvs update -r QA_2_0</command>
<prompt>$ </prompt><command>cvs tag RELEASE_2_0RC1</command>
...and then the actual release, from the same branch:
<prompt>$ </prompt><command>cvs tag RELEASE_2_0</command>
</screen>
    </informalexample>
    The "QA_2_0_BP" tag is a "branch point" tag, which is the start
    point of the tag.  It's always a good idea to start a CVS branch
    from such branch points.  MAINT branches may use the RELEASE tag
    as their branch point.
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.exampleurls">
   <title>Example URLs</title>
   <para>
    Use "example.com" for all example URLs, per RFC 2606.
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pear.standards.naming">
   <title>Naming Conventions</title>
   <sect2>
    <title>Functions and Methods</title>
    <para>
     Functions and methods should be named using the "studly caps"
     style (also referred to as "bumpy case" or "camel caps").
     Functions should in addition have the package name as a prefix,
     to avoid name collisions between packages.  The initial letter of
     the name (after the prefix) is lowercase, and each letter that
     starts a new "word" is capitalized.  Some examples:
     <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
       <tbody>
	<row>
	 <entry><simpara>connect()</simpara></entry>
	 <entry><simpara>getData()</simpara></entry>
	 <entry><simpara>buildSomeWidget()</simpara></entry>
	 <entry><simpara>XML_RPC_serializeData()</simpara></entry>
	</row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
     </informaltable>
    </para>
    <para>
     Private class members (meaning class members that are intented
     to be used only from within the same class in which they are
     declared; PHP does not yet support truly-enforceable private
     namespaces) are preceeded by a single underscore.  For example:
     <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
       <tbody>
	<row>
	 <entry><simpara>_sort()</simpara></entry>
	 <entry><simpara>_initTree()</simpara></entry>
	 <entry><simpara>$this->_status</simpara></entry>
	</row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
     </informaltable>
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
    <title>Constants</title>
    <para>
     Constants should always be all-uppercase, with underscores to
     seperate words.  Prefix constant names with the uppercased name
     of the class/package they are used in. For example, the constants
     used by the <literal>DB::</literal> package all begin with
     "<literal>DB_</literal>".
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
    <title>Global Variables</title>
    <para>
     If your package needs to define global variables, their name
     should start with a single underscore followed by the package
     name and another underscore.  For example, the PEAR package uses
     a global variable called $_PEAR_destructor_object_list.
    </para>
   </sect2>
  </sect1>

 </chapter>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"../../manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
