<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.1 $ -->
<sect1 id="install.unix.debian">
 <title>Debian GNU/Linux installation notes</title>
 <para>
  This section contains notes and hints specific to installing
  PHP on <ulink url="&url.debian;">Debian GNU/Linux</ulink>.
 </para>
 <sect2 id="install.unix.debian.apt">
  <title>Using APT</title>
   <simpara>
    While you can just download the PHP source and compile it yourself,
    using Debian's packaging system is the simplest and cleanest
    method of installing PHP. If you are not familiar with building
    software on Linux, this is the way to go.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    The first decision you need to make is whether you want to install
    Apache 1.3.x or Apache 2.x. The corresponding PHP packages are
    respectively named libapache-mod-php* and libapache2-mod-php*.
    The steps given below will use Apache 1.3.x.
    Please note that, as of this writing, there is no official 
    Debian packages of PHP5. Then the steps given below will install PHP4.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    PHP is available in Debian as CGI or CLI flavour too, named respectively
    php4-cgi and php4-cli. If you need them, you'll just have to reproduce the
    following steps with the good package names.
    Another special package you'd want to install is php4-pear. It contains a
    minimal PEAR installation and the <command>pear</command> commandline
    utility.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    If you need more recent packages of PHP than the Debian's stable ones
    or if some PHP modules lacks the Debian official repository, perhaps
    you should take a look at <ulink url="&url.apt-get;">http://www.apt-get.org/</ulink>. 
    One of the results found should be
    <ulink url="http://www.dotdeb.org/">Dotdeb</ulink>. This unofficial repository
    is maintained by <ulink url="mailto:gui@php.net">Guillaume Plessis</ulink>
    and contains Debian packages of the most recent versions of PHP4 and PHP5.
    To use it, just add the to following two lines to your
    <filename>/etc/apt/sources.lists</filename> and run <command>apt-get
    update</command> :
   </simpara>
   <example>
    <title>The two Dotdeb related lines</title>
    <programlisting role="shell">
<![CDATA[
deb http://packages.dotdeb.org stable all
deb-src http://packages.dotdeb.org stable all
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </example>
   <simpara>
    The last thing to consider is whether your list of packages is up to date. 
    If you have not updated it recently, you need to run <command>apt-get update</command>
    before anything else. This way, you will be using the most recent
    stable version of the Apache and PHP packages.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    Now that everything is in place, you can use the following example
    to install Apache and PHP:
   </simpara>
   <example id="install.unix.debian.apt.example">
    <title>Debian Install Example with Apache 1.3</title>
    <programlisting role="shell">
<![CDATA[
# apt-get install libapache-mod-php4
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </example>
   <simpara>
    APT will automatically install the PHP4 module for Apache 1.3, and all its
    dependencies and then activate it.  If you're not asked to restart Apache
    duringduring the install process, you'll have to do it manually :
   </simpara>
   <example id="install.unix.debian.apt.example2">
    <title>Stopping and starting Apache once PHP4 is installed</title>
    <programlisting role="shell">
<![CDATA[
# /etc/init.d/apache stop
# /etc/init.d/apache start
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </example>
 </sect2>
 <sect2 id="install.unix.debian.config">
  <title>Better control on configuration</title>
   <simpara>
    In the last section, PHP was installed without with only core modules.
    This may not be what you want and you will soon discover that you need 
    more activated modules, like MySQL, cURL, GD, etc.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    When you compile PHP from source yourself, you need to activate modules
    via the <command>configure</command> command. With APT, you just have
    to install additional packages. They're all named 'php4-*' (or 'php5-*' if
    you installed PHP5 from a third party repository).
   </simpara>
   <example id="install.unix.debian.config.example">
    <title>Getting the list of PHP additionnal packages</title>
    <programlisting role="shell">
<![CDATA[
# dpkg -l 'php4-*'
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </example>
   <simpara>
    As you can see from the last output, there's a lot of PHP modules that
    you can install (excluding the php4-cgi, php4-cli or php4-pear special
    packages).
    Look at them closely and choose what you need. If you choose a module and 
    you do not have the proper libraries, APT will automatically install all
    the dependencies for you.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    If you choose to add the MySQL, cURL and GD support to PHP the command
    will look something like this:
   </simpara>  
   <example id="install.unix.debian.config.example2">
    <title>Install PHP with MySQL, cURL and GD</title>
    <programlisting role="shell">
<![CDATA[
# apt-get install php4-mysql php4-curl php4-gd
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </example>
   <simpara>
    APT will automatically add the appropriate lines to your
    different &php.ini; (<filename>/etc/php4/apache/php.ini</filename>,
    <filename>/etc/php4/cgi/php.ini</filename>, etc).
   </simpara>
   <example id="install.unix.debian.config.example3">
    <title>These lines activate MySQL, cURL and GD into PHP</title>
    <programlisting role="shell">
<![CDATA[
extension=mysql.so
extension=curl.so
extension=gd.so
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </example>
   <simpara>
    You'll only have to stop/start Apache as previously to activate the modules.
   </simpara>
 </sect2>
 <sect2 id="install.unix.debian.faq">
  <title>Common Problems</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
     If you see the PHP source instead of the result the script should
     produce, APT has probably not included
     <filename>/etc/apache/conf.d/php4</filename> in your Apache 1.3
     configuration. Please ensure that the following line is present in your
     <filename>/etc/apache/httpd.conf</filename> file then stop/start Apache:
    </simpara>
   <example id="install.unix.debian.faq.example">
    <title>This line activates PHP4 into Apache</title>
    <programlisting role="shell">
<![CDATA[
# Include /etc/apache/conf.d/
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </example>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
     If you installed an additionnal module and if its functions are not
     available in your scripts, please ensure that the appropriate line is present in your
     &php.ini;, as seen before. APT may fail during the installation
     of the additionnal module, due to a confusing debconf configuration.
    </simpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect2>
</sect1>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"../../manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
