<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->
<!-- splitted from ./index.xml, last change in rev 1.66 -->
  <chapter xml:id="security.general" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
   <title>General considerations</title>
   <simpara>
    A completely secure system is a virtual impossibility, so an
    approach often used in the security profession is one of balancing
    risk and usability. If every variable submitted by a user required
    two forms of biometric validation (such as a retinal scan and a
    fingerprint), you would have an extremely high level of
    accountability. It would also take half an hour to fill out a fairly
    complex form, which would tend to encourage users to find ways of
    bypassing the security.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    The best security is often unobtrusive enough to suit the
    requirements without the user being prevented from accomplishing
    their work, or over-burdening the code author with excessive
    complexity. Indeed, some security attacks are merely exploits of
    this kind of overly built security, which tends to erode over time.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    A phrase worth remembering: A system is only as good as the weakest
    link in a chain. If all transactions are heavily logged based on
    time, location, transaction type, etc. but the user is only
    verified based on a single cookie, the validity of tying the users
    to the transaction log is severely weakened.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    When testing, keep in mind that you will not be able to test all
    possibilities for even the simplest of pages. The input you
    may expect will be completely unrelated to the input given by
    a disgruntled employee, a cracker with months of time on their
    hands, or a housecat walking across the keyboard. This is why it's
    best to look at the code from a logical perspective, to discern
    where unexpected data can be introduced, and then follow how it is
    modified, reduced, or amplified.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    The Internet is filled with people trying to make a name for
    themselves by breaking your code, crashing your site, posting
    inappropriate content, and otherwise making your day interesting.
    It doesn't matter if you have a small or large site, you are
    a target by simply being online, by having a server that can be
    connected to. Many cracking programs do not discern by size, they
    simply trawl massive IP blocks looking for victims. Try not to
    become one.
   </simpara>
  </chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
