<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.11 $ -->
<!-- Purpose: utilspec.windows -->
<!-- Membership: bundled -->

<reference id="ref.com"> 
  <title>COM and .Net (Windows)</title> 
  <titleabbrev>COM</titleabbrev> 
  <partintro> 
   <section id="com.intro">
    &reftitle.intro;
    <para>
     COM is an acronym for Component Object Model; it is an object orientated
     layer (and associated services) on top of DCE RPC (an open standard) and
     defines a common calling convention that enables code written in any
     language to call and interoperate with code written in any other language
     (provided those languages are COM aware).  Not only can the code be
     written in any language, but it need not even be part of the same
     executable; the code can be loaded from a DLL, be found in another
     process running on the same machine, or, with DCOM (Distributed COM), be
     found in another process on a remote machine, all without your code even
     needing to know where a component resides.
    </para>
    <para>
     There is a subset of COM known as OLE Automation which comprises a set of
     COM interfaces that allow loose binding to COM objects, so that they can
     be introspected and called at run-time without compile-time knowledge of
     how the object works.  The PHP COM extension utilizes the OLE
     Automation interfaces to allow you to create and call compatible objects
     from your scripts.  Technically speaking, this should really be called
     the "OLE Automation Extension for PHP", since not all COM objects are OLE
     compatible.
    </para>
    <para>
     Now, why would or should you use COM?  COM is one of the main ways to glue
     applications and components together on the Windows platform; using COM
     you can launch Microsoft Word, fill in a document template and save the
     result as a Word document and send it to a visitor of your web site.  You
     can also use COM to perform administrative tasks for your network and to
     configure your IIS; these are just the most common uses; you can do much
     more with COM.
    </para>
    <para>
     Starting with PHP 5, this extension (and this documentation) was
     rewritten from scratch and much of the old confusing and bogus cruft has
     be removed.  Additionally, we support the instantiation and creation of
     .Net assemblies using the COM interoperability layer provided by
     Microsoft.
    </para>
    <para> 
     Please read <ulink url="&url.zend.comdotnet;">this article</ulink>
     for an overview of the changes in this extension in PHP 5.
    </para>
   </section>

   <section id="com.requirements">
    &reftitle.required;
    <para>
     COM functions are only available for the Windows version of PHP.
    </para>
    <para>
     .Net support requires PHP 5 and the .Net runtime.
    </para> 
   </section>

   <section id="com.installation">
    &reftitle.install;
    &no.install;
    &windows.builtin;
    <para>
     You are responsible for installing support for the various COM objects
     that you intend to use (such as MS Word); we don't and can't bundle all
     of those with PHP.
    </para>
   </section>

   <section id="com.foreach">
    <title>For Each</title>

    <para>
     Starting with PHP 5, you may use PHP's own <xref
     linkend="control-structures.foreach"/> statement to iterate
     over the contents of a standard COM/OLE IEnumVariant.  In laymans terms,
     this means that you can use foreach in places where you would have used
     <literal>For Each</literal> in VB/ASP code.
    </para>

   <para>
    <example>
     <title>For Each in ASP</title>
     <programlisting role="asp">
<![CDATA[
<%
Set domainObject = GetObject("WinNT://Domain")
For Each obj in domainObject
  Response.Write obj.Name & "<br />"
Next
%>
]]>
     </programlisting>
    </example>
   </para>

   <para>
    <example>
     <title>while() ... Next() in PHP 4</title>
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php 
$domainObject = new COM("WinNT://Domain"); 
while ($obj = $domainObject->Next()) { 
   echo $obj->Name . "<br />"; 
} 
?>
]]>
     </programlisting>
    </example>
   </para>

   <para>
    <example>
     <title>foreach in PHP 5</title>
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php 
$domainObject = new COM("WinNT://Domain"); 
foreach ($domainObject as $obj) { 
   echo $obj->Name . "<br />"; 
} 
?>
]]>
     </programlisting>
    </example>
   </para>
   </section>

   <section id="com.arrays">
    <title>Arrays and Array-style COM properties</title>

    <para>
     Many COM objects expose their properties as arrays, or using array-style
     access.  In PHP 4, you may use PHP array syntax to read/write such a
     property, but only a single dimension is allowed.  If  you want to read a
     multi-dimensional property, you could instead make the property access
     into a function call, with each parameter representing each dimension of
     the array access, but there is no way to write to such a property.
    </para>

    <para>
     PHP 5 introduces the following new features to make your life easier:

     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Access multi-dimensional arrays, or COM properties that require
        multiple parameters using PHP array syntax.  You can also write or set
        properties using this technique.
       </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
       <para>
        Iterate SafeArrays ("true" arrays) using the <xref
        linkend="control-structures.foreach"/> control structure.  This works
        because SafeArrays include information about their size.  If an
        array-style property implements IEnumVariant then you can also use
        foreach for that property too; take a look at <xref
        linkend="com.foreach"/> for more information on this topic.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </para>

   </section>

   <section id="com.exceptions">
    <title>Exceptions (PHP 5)</title>

    <para>
     This extension will throw instances of the class <literal>com_exception</literal>
     whenever there is a potentially fatal error reported by COM.  All
     COM exceptions have a well-defined <literal>code</literal> property that
     corresponds to the HRESULT return value from the various COM operations.
     You may use this code to make programmatic decisions on how to handle the
     exception.
    </para>

   </section>

   &reference.com.ini;

   &reference.com.constants;
   
   <section id="com.seealso">
    &reftitle.seealso;
    <para>
     For further information on COM read the <ulink url="&url.comspecs;">COM
     specification</ulink> or perhaps take a look at Don Box's 
     <ulink url="&url.yacl;">Yet Another COM Library (YACL)</ulink>.
     You might find some additional useful information in our FAQ for <xref
     linkend="faq.com"/>.
     If you're thinking of using MS Office applications on the server side,
     you should read the information here: <ulink
     url="&url.msoffice.serverside;">Considerations for Server-Side Automation
     of Office</ulink>.
    </para> 
   </section>
  </partintro> 

&reference.com.functions;

</reference>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"../../../manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->

