<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<sect1 xml:id="language.operators.functional">
 <title>Functional Operators</title>
 <titleabbrev>Functional</titleabbrev>
 <para>
  PHP 8.5 and later supports one operator that works directly on callables.  The <literal>|&gt;</literal>
  operator, or “pipe,” accepts a single-parameter callable on the right and passes
  the left-side value to it, evaluating to the callable's result.  The callable
  on the right may be any valid PHP callable: a <classname>Closure</classname>,
  a <link linkend="functions.first_class_callable_syntax">first-class callable</link>,
  an object that implements <link linkend="object.invoke">__invoke()</link>, etc.
 </para>
 <para>
  That means the following two lines are logically equivalent.
  <example>
   <title>Using <literal>|&gt;</literal></title>
   <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php
$result = "Hello World" |> strlen(...);
echo $result, PHP_EOL;

$result = strlen("Hello World");
echo $result, PHP_EOL;
?>
]]>
   </programlisting>
   &example.outputs;
   <screen>
<![CDATA[
11
11
]]>
   </screen>
  </example>
 </para>
 <para>
  For a single call that is not especially useful. It becomes useful when multiple calls are chained together.
  That is, the following two code fragments are logically equivalent:
  <example>
   <title>Chaining |&gt; calls</title>
   <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php
$result = "PHP Rocks"
    |> htmlentities(...)
    |> str_split(...)
    |> (fn($x) => array_map(strtoupper(...), $x))
    |> (fn($x) => array_filter($x, fn($v) => $v != 'O'))
;
print_r($result);

$temp = "PHP Rocks";
$temp = htmlentities($temp);
$temp = str_split($temp);
$temp = array_map(strtoupper(...), $temp);
$temp = array_filter($temp, fn($v) => $v != 'O');
$result = $temp;
print_r($result);
?>
]]>
   </programlisting>
   &example.outputs;
   <screen>
<![CDATA[
Array
(
    [0] => P
    [1] => H
    [2] => P
    [3] =>
    [4] => R
    [6] => C
    [7] => K
    [8] => S
)
Array
(
    [0] => P
    [1] => H
    [2] => P
    [3] =>
    [4] => R
    [6] => C
    [7] => K
    [8] => S
)
]]>
   </screen>
  </example>
 </para>
 <para>
  The left-hand side of the pipe may be any value or expression.  The right-hand side
  may be any valid PHP callable that takes a single parameter, or any expression
  that evaluates to such a callable.  Functions with more than one required parameter
  are not allowed and will fail as if the function were called normally
  with insufficient arguments. Functions that take a variable by reference are not allowed.
  If the right-hand side does not evaluate to a valid callable it will throw an Error.
 </para>
 <note>
  <para>
   Be aware that, to avoid syntax ambiguity, <link linkend="functions.arrow">arrow functions</link>
   MUST be wrapped in parentheses when used with a pipe operator, as in the examples above.
   Failing to do so will result in a fatal error.
  </para>
 </note>

 <sect2 role="seealso">
  &reftitle.seealso;
  <para>
   <simplelist>
    <member><classname>Closure</classname></member>
   </simplelist>
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
