<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->

<section xml:id="mongo.readpreferences" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Read Preferences</title>
 <para>
  MongoDB 2.2 and version 1.3.0 of the driver add support for 
  <link xlink:href="&url.mongodb.docs.readpreferences;">read preferences</link>,
  which allow control over how queries are directed to mongod instances. Read
  preferences may be specified on either a per-connection, per-database,
  per-collection, or per-cursor basis. Preferences defined at a higher level
  will be inherited by default (e.g. <classname>MongoCollection</classname> will
  inherit read perferences defined on the corresponding
  <classname>MongoDB</classname> instance).
 </para>
 <para>
  Read preferences are specified with a combination of modes and tag sets. Modes
  determine how mongod instances are prioritized, while
  <link xlink:href="&url.mongodb.docs.tagsets;">tag sets</link> specify criteria
  for eligible mongod instances.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Read Preference Modes</title>
  <warning>
   <para>
    All read preference modes except <literal>Mongo::RP_PRIMARY</literal> may
    return stale data as secondaries replicate operations from the primary with
    some delay. Ensure that your application can tolerate stale data if you
    choose to use a mode other than <literal>Mongo::RP_PRIMARY</literal>.
   </para>
  </warning>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Mongo::RP_PRIMARY</literal>
    </para>
    <para>
     All read operations use only the current replica set primary. This is the
     default. If the primary is unavailable, read operations will produce an
     exception.
    </para>
    <para>
     This mode is incompatible with use of tag sets. Specifying a tag set with
     <literal>Mongo::RP_PRIMARY</literal> will result in an error.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Mongo::RP_PRIMARY_PREFERRED</literal>
    </para>
    <para>
     In most situations, operations read from the primary member of the set.
     However, if the primary is unavailable, as is the case during failover
     situations, operations read from secondary members.
    </para>
    <para>
     When the read preference includes a tag set, the client reads first from
     the primary, if available, and then from secondaries that match the
     specified tags. If no secondaries have matching tags, the read operation
     will produce an exception.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <para>
      Version 2.2 of mongos added full support for read preferences. When
      connecting to older mongos instances,
      <literal>Mongo::RP_PRIMARY_PREFERRED</literal> will send queries to
      secondaries.
     </para>
    </warning>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Mongo::RP_SECONDARY</literal>
    </para>
    <para>
     Operations read only from the secondary members of the set. If no
     secondaries are available, read operations will produce an exception.
    </para>
    <para>
     Most sets have at least one secondary, but there are situations where
     there may be no available secondary. For example, a set with a primary, a
     secondary, and an arbiter may not have any secondaries if a member is in
     recovering state or unavailable.
    </para>
    <para>
     When the read preference includes a tag set, the client attempts to find
     secondary members that match the specified tag set and directs reads to a
     random secondary from among the nearest group. If no secondaries have 
     matching tags, the read operation will produce an exception.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Mongo::RP_SECONDARY_PREFERRED</literal>
    </para>
    <para>
     In most situations, operations read from secondary members, but in
     situations where the set consists of a single primary with no other
     members, the read operation will use the set's primary.
    </para>
    <para>
     When the read preference includes a tag set, the client attempts to find a
     secondary member that matches the specified tag set and directs reads to a
     random secondary from among the nearest group. If no secondaries have
     matching tags, the read operation will produce an exception.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Mongo::RP_NEAREST</literal>
    </para>
    <para>
     The driver reads from the nearest member of the set according to the member
     selection process. Reads in the <literal>Mongo::RP_NEAREST</literal> mode
     do not consider the member's type and may read from both primaries and
     secondaries.
    </para>
    <para>
     Set this mode to minimize the effect of network latency on read operations
     without preference for current or stale data.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you specify a tag set, the client attempts to find a secondary member
     that matches the specified tag set and directs reads to a random secondary
     from among the nearest group.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      All operations read from the nearest member of the replica set that
      matches the specified read preference mode. The
      <literal>Mongo::RP_NEAREST</literal> mode prefers low latency reads over a
      member's primary or secondary status.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Tag Sets</title>
  <para>
   <link xlink:href="&url.mongodb.docs.tagsets;">Tag sets</link> allow you to
   specify criteria so that your application can target read operations to
   specific members, based on custom parameters. Tag sets make it possible to
   ensure that read operations target members in a particular data center or
   target mongod instances designated for a particular class of operations, such
   as reporting or analytics.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can specify tag sets with the following read preference modes:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Mongo::RP_PRIMARY_PREFERRED</literal>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Mongo::RP_SECONDARY</literal>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Mongo::RP_SECONDARY_PREFERRED</literal>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Mongo::RP_NEAREST</literal>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   You cannot specify tag sets with the <literal>Mongo::RP_PRIMARY</literal>
   read preference mode. Tags apply only when selecting a secondary member of a
   set, except for the when in the nearest mode.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Specifying Read Preferences</title>
  <para>
   Read preferences may be specified in either the connection URI provided to
   <function>Mongo::__construct</function>, which uses a query string syntax, or
   via setter methods on the core classes, which use an array syntax for tag
   sets.
  </para>
  <para>
   When specifying read preference modes in a query string, the names
   <literal>primary</literal>, <literal>primaryPreferred</literal>,
   <literal>secondary</literal>, <literal>secondaryPreferred</literal>, and
   <literal>nearest</literal> should be used instead of the constants for the
   <literal>readPreference</literal> value. Tag sets for the
   <literal>readPreferenceTags</literal> value should be a comma-delimited
   sequence of colon-delimited key/value pairs.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    Each tag set defined in the query string will use the
    <literal>readPreferenceTags</literal> name. Unlike how PHP might handle URL
    query strings, successive values for <literal>readPreferenceTags</literal>
    will not overwrite each other. The driver will collect tag sets in the order
    they appear in the query string.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   <example>
    <title>Connection URI read preferences with query string syntax</title>
    <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php

// Prefer the nearest server with no tag preference
$uri  = 'mongodb://rs1.example.com,rs2.example.com/';
$uri .= '?readPreference=nearest';
$m = new Mongo($uri, array('replicaSet' => 'rs'));

// Prefer the nearest server in the "east" data center
$uri  = 'mongodb://rs1.example.com,rs2.example.com/';
$uri .= '?readPreference=nearest';
$uri .= '&readPreferenceTags=dc:east';
$m = new Mongo($uri, array('replicaSet' => 'rs'));

// Prefer the nearest server in the "east" data center also used for reporting,
// but fall back to a server in the "west" data center
$uri  = 'mongodb://rs1.example.com,rs2.example.com/';
$uri .= '?readPreference=nearest';
$uri .= '&readPreferenceTags=dc:east,use:reporting';
$uri .= '&readPreferenceTags=dc:west';
$m = new Mongo($uri, array('replicaSet' => 'rs'));

// Prefer the nearest server in the "east" data center, then a server in the
// "west" data center, and finally fall back to no tag set preference
$uri  = 'mongodb://rs1.example.com,rs2.example.com/';
$uri .= '?readPreference=nearest';
$uri .= '&readPreferenceTags=dc:east';
$uri .= '&readPreferenceTags=dc:west';
$uri .= '&readPreferenceTags=';
$m = new Mongo($uri, array('replicaSet' => 'rs'));
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </example>
  </para>
  <para>
   <example>
    <title>Setting read preferences with array syntax for tag sets</title>
    <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php

$m = new Mongo('mongodb://rs1.example.com,rs2.example.com', array(
    'replicaSet' => 'rs',
));

// Prefer the nearest server with no tag preference
$m->setReadPreference(Mongo::RP_NEAREST, array());

// Prefer the nearest server in the "east" data center
$m->setReadPreference(Mongo::RP_NEAREST, array(
    array('dc' => 'east'),
));

// Prefer the nearest server in the "east" data center also used for reporting,
// but fall back to a server in the "west" data center
$m->setReadPreference(Mongo::RP_NEAREST, array(
    array('dc' => 'east', 'use' => 'reporting'),
    array('dc' => 'west'),
));

// Prefer the nearest server in the "east" data center, then a server in the
// "west" data center, and finally fall back to no tag set preference
$m->setReadPreference(Mongo::RP_NEAREST, array(
    array('dc' => 'east'),
    array('dc' => 'west'),
    array(),
));
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </example>
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
