<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->

<sect1 xml:id="function.return" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>return</title>
 <simpara>
  If called from within a function, the <function>return</function>
  statement immediately ends execution of the current function, and
  returns its argument as the value of the function
  call. <function>return</function> will also end the execution of
  an <function>eval</function> statement or script file.
 </simpara>
 <simpara>
  If called from the global scope, then execution of the current
  script file is ended. If the current script file was
  <function>include</function>ed or <function>require</function>ed,
  then control is passed back to the calling file. Furthermore, if
  the current script file was <function>include</function>ed, then
  the value given to <function>return</function> will be returned as
  the value of the <function>include</function> call. If
  <function>return</function> is called from within the main script
  file, then script execution ends. If the current script file was
  named by the <link
  linkend="ini.auto-prepend-file">auto_prepend_file</link> or <link
  linkend="ini.auto-append-file">auto_append_file</link>
  configuration options in &php.ini;,
  then that script file's execution is ended.
 </simpara>
 <simpara>For more information, see <link
 linkend="functions.returning-values">Returning values</link>.
 </simpara>
 <para>
  <note>
   <simpara>
    Note that since <function>return</function> is a language
    construct and not a function, the parentheses surrounding its
    arguments are not required. It is common to leave them out, and you
    actually should do so as PHP has less work to do in this case.
   </simpara>
  </note>
  <note>
   <simpara>
    If no parameter is supplied, then the parentheses must be omitted
    and <literal>NULL</literal> will be
    returned. Calling <function>return</function> with parentheses but
    with no arguments will result in a parse error.
   </simpara>
  </note>
  <note>
   <simpara>
    You should <emphasis>never</emphasis> use parentheses around your return
    variable when returning by reference, as this will not work. You can
    only return variables by reference, not the result of a statement. If
    you use <literal>return ($a);</literal> then you're not returning a
    variable, but the result of the expression <literal>($a)</literal>
    (which is, of course, the value of <varname>$a</varname>).
    </simpara>
   </note>
 </para>
</sect1>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
