<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->
 <sect1 xml:id="internals2.memory.management" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Basic memory management</title>

  <para>
   When programming in the C programming language the developer has to manually
   care about memory management. As PHP is usually used as a web server
   module memory management is from special relevance in order to prevent memory
   leaks. Additionally you should be aware that PHP might be used in threaded
   environments which means that global variables might lead to race
   conditions. For information about dealing with thread-global data please
   refer to the documentation on the <xref linkend="internals2.memory.TSRM"/>,
   which serves as thread-isolation facility.
  </para>

  <para>
   Additionally to these requirements the Zend Engine is faced with a quite
   special usage pattern where, within a relatively short time, many memory
   blocks of the size of a zval structure or  other small memory blocks are
   requested and freed again. Memory management in PHP has also to respect
   the <link linkend="ini.memory-limit">memory_limit</link>.
  </para>

  <para>
   For fulfilling the above requirements the Zend Engine provides a special
   memory manager for handling request-bound data. Request-bound data is data
   that is needed only for serving a single request and which will be freed at
   the request's end at latest. Extension authors will mostly only have contact 
   with the routines listed in the table below. Although they are implemented 
   as macros for providing some convenience features this documentation will 
   treat them like functions.
  </para>

  <table xml:id="internals2.memory.management.apis">
   <title>Main memory APIs</title>
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Prototype</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     
     <row>
      <entry><code>void *emalloc(size_t size)</code></entry>
      <entry>Allocate <code>size</code> bytes of memory.</entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry><code>void *ecalloc(size_t nmemb, size_t size)</code></entry>
      <entry>
       Allocate a buffer for <code>nmemb</code> elements of
       <code>size</code> bytes and makes sure it is initialized with zeros.
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry><code>void *erealloc(void *ptr, size_t size)</code></entry>
      <entry>
       Resize the buffer <code>ptr</code>, which was allocated using
       <code>emalloc</code> to hold <code>size</code> bytes of memory.
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry><code>void efree(void *ptr)</code></entry>
      <entry>
       Free the buffer pointed by <code>ptr</code>. The buffer had to be 
       allocated by <code>emalloc</code>.
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry>
       <code>void *safe_emalloc(size_t nmemb, size_t size, size_t offset)</code>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       Allocate a buffer for holding <code>nmemb</code> blocks of each
       <code>size</code> bytes and an additional <code>offset</code> bytes.
       This is similar to <code>emalloc(nmemb * size + offset)</code> but adds
       a special protection against overflows.
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry><code>char *estrdup(const char *s)</code></entry>
      <entry>
       Allocate a buffer that can hold the NULL-terminated string
       <code>s</code> and copy the <code>s</code> into that buffer.
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry>
       <code>char *estrndup(const char *s, unsigned int length)</code>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       Similar to <code>estrdup</code> while the length of the
       NULL-terminated string is already known.
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <note>
   <simpara>
    Unlike their C standard library's counterparts the Zend Engine's memory
    management functions won't return NULL in case of an problem while 
    allocating the requested memory but bail out and terminate the current 
    request.
   </simpara>
  </note>

  <para>
   As said above it is an essential part of the memory management to avoid
   having memory leaks and therefore free all memory you've allocated as soon
   as possible. As a safety net the Zend Engine will free all memory, which had
   been allocated using above mentioned APIs at the end of a request. If PHP 
   was built using the <code>--enable-debug</code> configuration option this 
   will lead to a warning.
  </para>

  <example xml:id="internals2.memory.management.example.leak">
   <title>PHP's leak warnings</title>
   <programlisting role="c">
<![CDATA[
ZEND_FUNCTION(leak)
{
    long leakbytes = 3;

    if (zend_parse_parameters(ZEND_NUM_ARGS() TSRMLS_CC, "|l", &leakbytes) == FAILURE) {
        return;
    }

    emalloc(leakbytes);
}
]]>
   </programlisting>
   &example.outputs.similar;
   <screen>
<![CDATA[
[Thu Oct 22 02:14:57 2009]  Script:  '-'
/home/johannes/src/PHP_5_3/Zend/zend_builtin_functions.c(1377) :  Freeing 0x088888D4 (3 bytes), script=-
=== Total 1 memory leaks detected ===
]]>
   </screen>
  </example>

  <note>
   <simpara>
    When dealing with PHP variables you have to make sure the variable's
    memory is allocated using emalloc and take care of the reference count.
    Details can be found in <xref linkend="internals2.variables"/>.
   </simpara>
  </note>

  <note>
   <simpara>
    This leak detection can only find leaks caused by blocks allocated by 
    emalloc. You're advised to use a memory checker like valgrind or libumem
    for deeper analysis. To simplify the analysis PHP's memory manager can be 
    disabled by setting the environment variable USE_ZEND_ALLOC=0 before 
    starting PHP.
   </simpara>
  </note>

 </sect1>
 
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
