<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->
 <chapter xml:id="introduction" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <info><title>Introduction</title></info>

  <section xml:id="intro-whatis">
   <info><title>What is PHP?</title></info>
   <para>
    <acronym>PHP</acronym> (recursive acronym for <literal>PHP: Hypertext
    Preprocessor</literal>) is a widely-used open source general-purpose
    scripting language that is especially suited for web
    development and can be embedded into HTML.
   </para>
   <para>
    Nice, but what does that mean? An example:
   </para>
   <para>
    <example>
     <info><title>An introductory example</title></info>
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.01 Transitional//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/loose.dtd">
<html>
    <head>
        <title>Example</title>
    </head>
    <body>

        <?php
            echo "Hi, I'm a PHP script!";
        ?>

    </body>
</html>
]]>
     </programlisting>
    </example>
   </para>
   <para>
    Instead of lots of commands to output HTML (as seen in C or Perl),
    PHP pages contain HTML with embedded code that does
    "something" (in this case, output "Hi, I'm a PHP script!").
    The PHP code is enclosed in special <link
    linkend="language.basic-syntax.phpmode">start and end processing
    instructions <code>&lt;?php</code> and <code>?&gt;</code></link>
    that allow you to jump into and out of "PHP mode."
   </para>
   <para>
    What distinguishes PHP from something like client-side JavaScript
    is that the code is executed on the server, generating HTML which
    is then sent to the client. The client would receive
    the results of running that script, but would not know
    what the underlying code was. You can even configure your web server
    to process all your HTML files with PHP, and then there's really no
    way that users can tell what you have up your sleeve.
   </para>
   <para>
    The best things in using PHP are that it is extremely simple
    for a newcomer, but offers many advanced features for
    a professional programmer. Don't be afraid reading the long
    list of PHP's features. You can jump in, in a short time, and
    start writing simple scripts in a few hours.
   </para>
   <para>
    Although PHP's development is focused on server-side scripting,
    you can do much more with it. Read on, and see more in the
    <link linkend="intro-whatcando">What can PHP do?</link> section,
    or go right to the <link linkend="tutorial">introductory
    tutorial</link> if you are only interested in web programming.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="intro-whatcando">
   <info><title>What can PHP do?</title></info>
   <para>
    Anything. PHP is mainly focused on server-side scripting,
    so you can do anything any other CGI program can do, such
    as collect form data, generate dynamic page content, or
    send and receive cookies. But PHP can do much more.
   </para>
   <para>
    There are three main areas where PHP scripts are used.
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
       Server-side scripting. This is the most traditional
       and main target field for PHP. You need three things
       to make this work. The PHP parser (CGI or server
       module), a web server and a web browser. You need to
       run the web server, with a connected PHP installation.
       You can access the PHP program output with a web browser,
       viewing the PHP page through the server. All these can
       run on your home machine if you are just experimenting
       with PHP programming. See the
       <link linkend="install">installation instructions</link>
       section for more information.
      </simpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
       Command line scripting. You can make a PHP script
       to run it without any server or browser.
       You only need the PHP parser to use it this way.
       This type of usage is ideal for scripts regularly
       executed using cron (on *nix or Linux) or Task Scheduler (on
       Windows). These scripts can also be used for simple text
       processing tasks. See the section about
       <link linkend="features.commandline">Command line usage of PHP</link>
       for more information.
      </simpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
       Writing desktop applications. PHP is probably
       not the very best language to create a desktop
       application with a graphical user interface, but if
       you know PHP very well, and would like to use some
       advanced PHP features in your client-side applications
       you can also use PHP-GTK to write such programs. You also
       have the ability to write cross-platform applications this
       way. PHP-GTK is an extension to PHP, not available in
       the main distribution. If you are interested
       in PHP-GTK, visit <link xlink:href="&url.php.gtk;">its
       own website</link>.
      </simpara>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </para>
   <para>
    PHP can be used on all major operating systems, including
    Linux, many Unix variants (including HP-UX, Solaris and OpenBSD),
    Microsoft Windows, Mac OS X, RISC OS, and probably others.
    PHP has also support for most of the web servers today. This
    includes Apache, Microsoft Internet Information Server,
    Personal Web Server, Netscape and iPlanet servers, Oreilly
    Website Pro server, Caudium, Xitami, OmniHTTPd, and many
    others. For the majority of the servers, PHP has a module,
    for the others supporting the CGI standard, PHP can work
    as a CGI processor.
   </para>
   <para>
    So with PHP, you have the freedom of choosing an operating
    system and a web server. Furthermore, you also have the choice
    of using procedural programming or object oriented
    programming, or a mixture of them. Although not every
    standard OOP feature is implemented in PHP 4,
    many code libraries and large applications (including
    the PEAR library) are written only using OOP code. PHP 5 fixes the
    OOP related weaknesses of PHP 4, and introduces a complete object
    model.
   </para>
   <para>
    With PHP you are not limited to output HTML. PHP's abilities
    includes outputting images, PDF files and even Flash movies
    (using libswf and Ming) generated on the fly. You can also
    output easily any text, such as XHTML and any other XML file.
    PHP can autogenerate these files, and save them in the file
    system, instead of printing it out, forming a server-side
    cache for your dynamic content.
   </para>
   <para>
    One of the strongest and most significant features in PHP is its
    support for a wide range of databases. Writing a database-enabled
    web page is incredibly simple. The following databases are currently
    supported:
    <blockquote>
     <simplelist columns="3">
      <member>Adabas D</member>
      <member>dBase</member>
      <member>Empress</member>
      <member>FilePro (read-only)</member>
      <member>Hyperwave</member>
      <member>IBM DB2</member>
      <member>Informix</member>
      <member>Ingres</member>
      <member>InterBase</member>
      <member>FrontBase</member>
      <member>mSQL</member>
      <member>Direct MS-SQL</member>
      <member>MySQL</member>
      <member>ODBC</member>
      <member>Oracle (OCI7 and OCI8)</member>
      <member>Ovrimos</member>
      <member>PostgreSQL</member>
      <member>SQLite</member>
      <member>Solid</member>
      <member>Sybase</member>
      <member>Velocis</member>
      <member>Unix dbm</member>
     </simplelist>
    </blockquote>
    We also have a database abstraction extension (named PDO) allowing you
    to transparently use any database supported by that extension.
    Additionally PHP supports ODBC, the Open Database Connection
    standard, so you can connect to any other database supporting
    this world standard.
   </para>
   <para>
    PHP also has support for talking to other services using protocols
    such as LDAP, IMAP, SNMP, NNTP, POP3, HTTP, COM (on Windows) and
    countless others. You can also open raw network sockets and
    interact using any other protocol. PHP has support for the WDDX
    complex data exchange between virtually all Web programming
    languages. Talking about interconnection, PHP has support for
    instantiation of Java objects and using them transparently
    as PHP objects. You can also use our CORBA extension to
    access remote objects.
   </para>
   <para>
    PHP has extremely useful text processing features, from the
    POSIX Extended or Perl regular expressions to parsing XML
    documents. For parsing and accessing XML documents, PHP 4
    supports the SAX and DOM standards, and you can also use the
    XSLT extension to transform XML documents. PHP 5 standardizes
    all the XML extensions on the solid base of libxml2 and extends
    the feature set adding SimpleXML and XMLReader support.
   </para>
   <para>
    At last but not least, we have many other interesting
    extensions, the mnoGoSearch search engine functions,
    the IRC Gateway functions, many compression utilities
    (gzip, bz2, zip), calendar conversion, translation...
   </para>
   <para>
    As you can see this page is not enough to list all
    the features and benefits PHP can offer. Read on in
    the sections about <link linkend="install">installing
    PHP</link>, and see the <link linkend="funcref">function
    reference</link> part for explanation of the extensions
    mentioned here.
   </para>
  </section>

 </chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
