<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->
<chapter xml:id="introduction"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

  <info>
    <title>What is PHP and what can it do?</title>
    <titleabbrev>Introduction</titleabbrev>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================
       SECTION: What is PHP?
       ================================ -->
  <section xml:id="intro-whatis" annotations="chunk:false">
    <info>
      <title>What is PHP?</title>
    </info>

    <para>
      <acronym>PHP</acronym> (a recursive acronym for
      <emphasis>PHP: Hypertext Preprocessor</emphasis>)
      is a widely used open-source general-purpose scripting language
      especially suited for web development, and it can be embedded directly into HTML.
    </para>

    <para>
      What does that mean in practice? Consider the following example:
    </para>

    <example>
      <info><title>An introductory example</title></info>
      <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
<!DOCTYPE html>
<html>
<head>
    <title>Example</title>
</head>
<body>

<?php
    echo "Hi, I'm a PHP script!";
?>

</body>
</html>
      ]]></programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>
      Instead of using many commands to output HTML (as in languages such as C or Perl),
      PHP pages contain regular HTML with embedded code that performs
      <replaceable>actions</replaceable> (in this case, outputting
      <computeroutput>Hi, I'm a PHP script!</computeroutput>).
      The PHP code is enclosed within special processing instructions
      <code>&lt;?php</code> and <code>?&gt;</code> that allow switching into and out of
      <quote>PHP mode</quote>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Unlike client-side JavaScript, PHP code is executed on the server,
      generating HTML that is then sent to the client. The client sees
      only the final output and not the underlying PHP code.
      A web server can even be configured to process all HTML files through PHP,
      making it impossible for users to know that PHP is being used.
    </para>

    <para>
      One advantage of PHP is that it is extremely simple for beginners
      while still offering advanced features for experienced developers.
      With PHP, almost anyone can begin writing useful scripts quickly.
    </para>

    <para>
      Although PHP’s primary focus is server-side scripting,
      it is capable of much more. You can read more in the
      <link linkend="intro-whatcando">What can PHP do?</link> section,
      or jump straight into the <link linkend="tutorial">introductory tutorial</link>
      to start learning web programming.
    </para>

  </section>

  <!-- ================================
       SECTION: What can PHP do?
       ================================ -->
  <section xml:id="intro-whatcando" annotations="chunk:false">
    <info>
      <title>What can PHP do?</title>
    </info>

    <para>
      PHP is capable of performing anything that other CGI programs can do,
      such as collecting form data, generating dynamic page content,
      or sending and receiving cookies. However, PHP goes far beyond these capabilities.
    </para>

    <para>
      PHP scripts are mainly used in two primary areas:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Server-side scripting.</emphasis>
          This is PHP’s most common use case. To run server-side scripts,
          you need three components: the PHP parser (as a CGI binary or a server module),
          a web server, and a web browser. All of these can run locally for testing and development.
          For details, refer to the <link linkend="install">installation instructions</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Command-line scripting.</emphasis>
          PHP scripts can also run on the command line, without any web server or browser.
          This is ideal for scripts executed using tools such as <command>cron</command>
          on Unix/macOS or Task Scheduler on Windows.
          PHP is also suitable for text-processing tasks.
          See <link linkend="features.commandline">Command line usage of PHP</link> for more information.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      PHP runs on all major operating systems, including Linux, numerous Unix variants
      (such as HP-UX, Solaris, and OpenBSD), Microsoft Windows, macOS, and others.
      It also supports a wide range of web servers including Apache, IIS, lighttpd, and nginx.
      PHP can operate either as a module or as a CGI/FastCGI processor.
    </para>

    <para>
      PHP gives developers the freedom to choose their operating system,
      web server, and programming paradigm. You may write procedural code,
      object-oriented programs, or a combination of both.
    </para>

    <para>
      PHP is not limited to generating HTML. It can create images, PDF files,
      and other rich content types; encrypt data; and send emails.
      It can output text formats such as XML or JSON and can generate files for
      server-side caching.
    </para>

    <para>
      One of PHP’s strongest features is its support for a
      <link linkend="refs.database">wide range of databases</link>.
      Using extensions such as <link linkend="book.mysqli">MySQLi</link>,
      abstraction layers such as <link linkend="book.pdo">PDO</link>,
      or the <link linkend="book.uodbc">ODBC</link> extension,
      making database-enabled web pages becomes straightforward.
      Other databases can be accessed using <link linkend="book.curl">cURL</link>
      or <link linkend="book.sockets">sockets</link>, such as CouchDB.
    </para>

    <para>
      PHP supports communication with services using protocols such as LDAP,
      IMAP, SNMP, NNTP, POP3, HTTP, COM (on Windows), and more.
      It can also open raw network sockets for custom protocols.
      PHP supports WDDX for data exchange between different programming languages.
      It can instantiate Java objects and interact with them through a PHP interface.
    </para>

    <para>
      PHP includes powerful <link linkend="refs.basic.text">text processing</link> features,
      including PCRE-compatible regular expressions
      (<link linkend="book.pcre">PCRE</link>)
      and multiple extensions for working with XML. XML functionality is built on
      <link linkend="book.libxml">libxml2</link> and includes
      <link linkend="book.simplexml">SimpleXML</link>,
      <link linkend="book.xmlreader">XMLReader</link>,
      and <link linkend="book.xmlwriter">XMLWriter</link>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Many other useful extensions exist, listed both
      <link linkend="extensions">alphabetically</link>
      and by <link linkend="funcref">category</link>.
      Additional extensions are available through PECL
      (<link linkend="install.pecl.intro">PECL extensions</link>),
      including tools such as Xdebug.
    </para>

    <para>
      This chapter cannot list every feature PHP offers. Read the sections on
      <link linkend="install">installing PHP</link> and consult the
      <link linkend="funcref">function reference</link> for more details
      about the features and extensions mentioned here.
    </para>

  </section>

</chapter>
