<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.24 $ -->
 <chapter id="tutorial">
  <title>A simple tutorial</title>

  <para>
   Here we would like to show the very basics of PHP in a short simple
   tutorial. This text only deals with dynamic webpage creation with
   PHP, though PHP is not only capable of creating webpages. See
   the section titled <link linkend="intro-whatcando">What can PHP
   do</link> for more information.
  </para>
  <para>
   PHP-enabled web pages are treated just like regular HTML pages and
   you can create and edit them the same way you normally create
   regular HTML pages.
  </para>

  <sect1 id="tutorial.requirements">
   <title>What do I need?</title>
   <para>
    In this tutorial we assume that your server has support for PHP
    activated and that all files ending in <filename>.php</filename>
    are handled by PHP. On most servers this is the default extension
    for PHP files, but ask your server administrator to be sure. If
    your server supports PHP then you don't need to do anything. Just
    create your <filename>.php</filename> files and put them in your
    web directory and the server will magically parse them for you.
    There is no need to compile anything nor do you need to install
    any extra tools. Think of these PHP-enabled files as simple HTML
    files with a whole new family of magical tags that let you do all
    sorts of things.  Most web hosts offer PHP support but if your
    host doesn't consider reading the <ulink url="&url.php.links;">
    PHP Links</ulink> section for resources on finding PHP enabled
    web hosts.
   </para>
   <para>
    Let's say you want to save precious bandwidth and develop locally.  
    In this case, you'll want to install a web server, such as 
    <link linkend="install.apache">Apache</link>, and of course 
    <ulink url="&url.php.downloads;">PHP</ulink>.  You'll most likely 
    want to install a database as well, such as 
    <ulink url="&url.mysql.docs;">MySQL</ulink>.  You can install 
    these individually or a simpler way is to <ulink
    url="&url.installkits;">locate a pre-configured package</ulink> 
    that automatically installs all of these with just a few mouse
    clicks.  It's easy to setup a web server with PHP support on
    any operating system, including Linux and Windows.  In Linux,
    you may find <ulink url="&url.rpmfind;">rpmfind</ulink> and
    <ulink url="&url.rpmfind.pbone;">PBone</ulink> helpful for
    locating RPMs.
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="tutorial.firstpage">
   <title>Your first PHP-enabled page</title>
   <para>
    Create a file named <filename>hello.php</filename> and put it
    in your web servers root directory (<varname>DOCUMENT_ROOT</varname>) 
    with the following content:
   </para>
   <para>
    <example>
     <title>Our first PHP script: <filename>hello.php</filename></title>
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<html>
 <head>
  <title>PHP Test</title>
 </head>
 <body>
 <?php echo "<p>Hello World</p>"; ?>
 </body>
</html>
]]>
     </programlisting>
     <simpara>
      Use your browser to access the file with your web access URL, ending
      with the "/hello.php" file reference.  When developing locally this
      url will be something like <literal>http://localhost/hello.php</literal> 
      or <literal>http://127.0.0.1/hello.php</literal> but this depends on the
      web servers configuration.  Although this is outside the scope of this
      tutorial, see also the <varname>DocumentRoot</varname> and
      <varname>ServerName</varname> directives in your web servers
      configuration file. (on Apache this is &httpd.conf;).
      If everything is setup correctly, this file will be parsed by PHP and
      the following output will make it to your browser:
     </simpara>
     <screen role="html">
<![CDATA[
<html>
 <head>
  <title>PHP Test</title>
 </head>
 <body>
 <p>Hello World</p>
 </body>
</html>
]]>
     </screen>
    </example>
   </para>
   <para>
    Note that this is not like a CGI script. The file does not need to be
    executable or special in any way. Think of it as a normal HTML
    file which happens to have a set of special tags available to you
    that do a lot of interesting things.
   </para>
   <para>
    This program is extremely simple and you really didn't need to use
    PHP to create a page like this. All it does is display:
    <literal>Hello World</literal> using the PHP <function>echo</function>
    statement.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you tried this example and it didn't output anything, or it prompted 
    for download, or you see the whole file as text, chances are that the 
    server you are on does not have PHP enabled. Ask your administrator 
    to enable it for you using the
    <link linkend="installation">Installation</link> chapter 
    of the manual.  If you're developing locally, also read the
    installation chapter to make sure everything is configured
    properly.  If problems continue to persist, don't hesitate to use one of
    the many <ulink url="&url.php.support;">PHP support</ulink> options.
   </para>
   <para>
    The point of the example is to show the special PHP tag format.
    In this example we used <literal>&lt;?php</literal> to indicate the
    start of a PHP tag. Then we put the PHP statement and left PHP mode by
    adding the closing tag, <literal>?&gt;</literal>. You may jump in
    and out of PHP mode in an HTML file like this all you want.  For more
    details, read the manual section on <link linkend="language.basic-syntax">
    basic PHP syntax</link>.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>A Note on Text Editors</title>
    <para>
     There are many text editors and Integrated Development Environments (IDEs)
     that you can use to create, edit and manage PHP files. A partial list of 
     these tools is maintained at <ulink url="&url.phpeditorlist;">PHP Editor's
     List</ulink>. If you wish to recommend an editor, please visit the above
     page and ask the page maintainer to add the editor to the list.  Having
     an editor with syntax highlighting can be helpful.
    </para>
   </note>
   
   <note>
    <title>A Note on Word Processors</title>
    <para>
     Word processors such as StarOffice Writer, Microsoft Word and Abiword are
     not good choices for editing PHP files.  If you wish to use one for this 
     test script, you must ensure that you save the file as PLAIN TEXT or PHP 
     will not be able to read and execute the script.
    </para>
   </note>
   
   <note>
    <title>A Note on Windows Notepad</title>
    <para>    
     If you are writing your PHP scripts using Windows Notepad, you will need
     to ensure that your files are saved with the .php extension. (Notepad adds
     a .txt extension to files automatically unless you take one of the
     following steps to prevent it.)  When you save the file and are prompted
     to provide a name for the file, place the filename in quotes 
     (i.e. "<filename>hello.php</filename>").  Alternately, you can click on the 
     'Text Documents' drop-down menu in the save dialog box and change the setting 
     to "All Files". You can then enter your filename without quotes.
    </para>
  </note>
  
  <para>
   Now that you've successfully created a simple PHP script that works, it's
   time to create the most famous PHP script!  Make a call to the
   <function>phpinfo</function> function and you'll see a lot of useful
   information about your system and setup such as available
   <link linkend="language.variables.predefined">Predefined Variables</link>, 
   loaded PHP modules, and <link linkend="configuration">configuration</link>
   settings.  Take some time and review this important information.
  </para>
   
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="tutorial.useful">
   <title>Something Useful</title>
   <para>
    Let's do something a bit more useful now. We are going to check
    what sort of browser the person viewing the page is using.
    In order to do that we check the user agent string that the browser
    sends as part of its HTTP request. This information is stored in a <link
    linkend="language.variables">variable</link>. Variables always start
    with a dollar-sign in PHP. The variable we are interested in right now 
    is <varname>$_SERVER["HTTP_USER_AGENT"]</varname>.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     <link linkend="reserved.variables.server">$_SERVER</link> is a 
     special reserved PHP variable that contains all web server information.
     It's known as an Autoglobal (or Superglobal).  See the related manual page on
     <link linkend="language.variables.superglobals">Autoglobals</link>
     for more information.  These special variables were introduced in PHP 
     <ulink url="&url.php.release4.1.0;">4.1.0</ulink>.  Before this time, we used
     the older <varname>$HTTP_*_VARS</varname> arrays instead,
     such as <varname>$HTTP_SERVER_VARS</varname>.  Although deprecated, 
     these older variables still exist.  (See also the note on
     <link linkend="tutorial.oldcode">old code</link>.)
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    To display this variable, we can simply do:
   </para>
   <para>
    <example>
    <title>Printing a variable (Array element)</title>
    <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php echo $_SERVER["HTTP_USER_AGENT"]; ?>
]]>
    </programlisting>
    <para>
     A sample output of this script may be:
    </para>
    <screen role="html">
Mozilla/4.0 (compatible; MSIE 5.01; Windows NT 5.0)
    </screen>
   </example>
   </para>
   <para>
    There are many <link linkend="language.types">types</link> of 
    variables available in PHP.  In the above example we printed 
    an <link linkend="language.types.array">Array</link> element.
    Arrays can be very useful.
   </para>
   <para>
    <varname>$_SERVER</varname> is just one variable that's automatically 
    made available to you by PHP.  A list can be seen in the 
    <link linkend="reserved.variables">Reserved Variables</link> section 
    of the manual or you can get a complete list of them by creating
    a file that looks like this:
   </para>
   <para>
    <example>
     <title>Show all predefined variables with <function>phpinfo</function></title>
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php phpinfo(); ?>
]]>
     </programlisting>
    </example>
   </para>
   <para>
    If you load up this file in your browser you will see a page
    full of information about PHP along with a list of all the
    variables available to you.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can put multiple PHP statements inside a PHP tag and create
    little blocks of code that do more than just a single echo.
    For example, if we wanted to check for Internet Explorer we
    could do something like this:
   </para>
   <para>
    <example>
     <title>Example using <link linkend="control-structures">control 
     structures</link> and <link linkend="functions">functions</link></title>
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php
if (strstr($_SERVER["HTTP_USER_AGENT"], "MSIE")) {
	echo "You are using Internet Explorer<br />";
}
?>
]]>
     </programlisting>
     <para>
      A sample output of this script may be:
     </para>
     <screen role="html">
<![CDATA[
You are using Internet Explorer<br />
]]>
     </screen>
    </example>
   </para>
   <para>
    Here we introduce a couple of new concepts. We have an 
    <link linkend="control-structures.if">if</link> statement.
    If you are familiar with the basic syntax used by the C
    language this should look logical to you. If you don't know enough
    C or some other language where the syntax used above is used, you
    should probably pick up any introductory PHP book and read the first
    couple of chapters, or read the <link linkend="langref">Language
    Reference</link> part of the manual. You can find a list of PHP books
    at <ulink url="&url.php.books;">&url.php.books;</ulink>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The second concept we introduced was the <function>strstr</function>
    function call. <function>strstr</function> is a function built into
    PHP which searches a string for another string. In this case we are
    looking for <literal>"MSIE"</literal> inside
    <varname>$_SERVER["HTTP_USER_AGENT"]</varname>. If the string is found,
    the function returns &true; and if it isn't, it returns &false;. If
    it returns &true;, the <link linkend="control-structures.if">if</link> 
    statement evaluates to &true; and the code within its {braces} is 
    executed.  Otherwise, it's not.  Feel free to create similar examples, 
    with <link linkend="control-structures.if">if</link>, 
    <link linkend="control-structures.else">else</link>, and other 
    functions such as <function>strtoupper</function> and 
    <function>strlen</function>.  Each related manual page contains examples 
    too.  If you're unsure how to use functions, you'll want to read both
    the manual page on <link linkend="about.prototypes">how to read a
    function definition</link> and the section about  
    <link linkend="functions">PHP functions</link>.
   </para>
   <para>
    We can take this a step further and show how you can jump in and out
    of PHP mode even in the middle of a PHP block:
   </para>
   <para>
    <example>
     <title>Mixing both HTML and PHP modes</title>
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
<?php
if (strstr($_SERVER["HTTP_USER_AGENT"], "MSIE")) {
?>
<h3>strstr must have returned true</h3>
<center><b>You are using Internet Explorer</b></center>
<?php
} else {
?>
<h3>strstr must have returned false</h3>
<center><b>You are not using Internet Explorer</b></center>
<?php
}
?>
]]>
     </programlisting>
     <para>
      A sample output of this script may be:
     </para>
     <screen role="html">
<![CDATA[
<h3>strstr must have returned true</h3>
<center><b>You are using Internet Explorer</b></center>
]]>
     </screen>
    </example>
   </para>
   <para>
    Instead of using a PHP echo statement to output something, we jumped out of PHP
    mode and just sent straight HTML. The important and powerful point to note here
    is that the logical flow of the script remains intact. Only one of the HTML blocks
    will end up getting sent to the viewer depending on if
    <function>strstr</function> returned &true; or &false;  In other words, 
    if the string <literal>MSIE</literal> was found or not.
   </para>
  </sect1>
   
  <sect1 id="tutorial.forms">
   <title>Dealing with Forms</title>
   <para>
    One of the most powerful features of PHP is the way it handles HTML
    forms. The basic concept that is important to understand is that any
    form element in a form will automatically be available to your PHP 
    scripts.  Please read the manual section on
    <link linkend="language.variables.external">Variables from outside 
    of PHP</link> for more information and examples on using forms 
    with PHP.  Here's an example HTML form:
   </para>
   <para>
    <example>
     <title>A simple HTML form</title>
     <programlisting role="html">
<![CDATA[
<form action="action.php" method="POST">
 Your name: <input type="text" name="name" />
 Your age: <input type="text" name="age" />
 <input type="submit">
</form>
]]>
     </programlisting>
    </example>
   </para>
   <para>
    There is nothing special about this form. It is a straight HTML form
    with no special tags of any kind. When the user fills in this form
    and hits the submit button, the <filename>action.php</filename> page
    is called. In this file you would have something like this:
   </para>
   <para>
    <example>
     <title>Printing data from our form</title>
     <programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[
Hi <?php echo $_POST["name"]; ?>.
You are <?php echo $_POST["age"]; ?> years old.
]]>
     </programlisting>
     <para>
      A sample output of this script may be:
     </para>
     <screen role="html">
<![CDATA[
Hi Joe.
You are 22 years old.
]]>
     </screen>
    </example>
   </para>
   <para>
    It should be obvious what this does. There is nothing more to it.
    The <varname>$_POST["name"]</varname> and <varname>$_POST["age"]</varname>
    variables are automatically set for you by PHP.  Earlier we
    used the <varname>$_SERVER</varname> autoglobal, now above we just 
    introduced the <link linkend="reserved.variables.post">$_POST</link>
    autoglobal which contains all POST data.  Notice how the
    <emphasis>method</emphasis> of our form is POST.  If we used the 
    method <emphasis>GET</emphasis> then our form information would live in 
    the <link linkend="reserved.variables.get">$_GET</link> autoglobal instead.
    You may also use the <link linkend="reserved.variables.request">$_REQUEST</link>
    autoglobal if you don't care the source of your request data. It 
    contains a mix of GET, POST and COOKIE data.  See also the 
    <function>import_request_variables</function> function.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="tutorial.oldcode">
   <title>Using old code with new versions of PHP</title>
   <para>
    Now that PHP has grown to be a popular scripting language, there are
    more resources out there that have listings of code you can reuse
    in your own scripts. For the most part the developers of the PHP
    language have tried to be backwards compatible, so a script written
    for an older version should run (ideally) without changes in a newer
    version of PHP, in practice some changes will usually be needed.
   </para>
   <para>
    Two of the most important recent changes that affect old code are:
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
       The deprecation of the old <varname>$HTTP_*_VARS</varname> arrays
       (which need to be indicated as global when used inside a function or
       method).  The following 
       <link linkend="language.variables.superglobals">autoglobal arrays</link>
       were introduced in PHP <ulink url="&url.php.release4.1.0;">4.1.0</ulink>. 
       They are: <varname>$_GET</varname>, <varname>$_POST</varname>, 
       <varname>$_COOKIE</varname>, <varname>$_SERVER</varname>, 
       <varname>$_FILES</varname>, <varname>$_ENV</varname>,
       <varname>$_REQUEST</varname>, and <varname>$_SESSION</varname>.  The
       older <varname>$HTTP_*_VARS</varname> arrays, such as
       <varname>$HTTP_POST_VARS</varname>, still exist and have since PHP 3. 
       
       &avail.register-long-arrays;
      </simpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
       External variables are no longer registered in the global scope by
       default.  In other words, as of PHP
       <ulink url="&url.php.release4.2.0;">4.2.0</ulink> the PHP directive 
       <link linkend="ini.register-globals">register_globals</link> is 
       <emphasis>off</emphasis> by default in &php.ini;. The preferred 
       method of accessing these values is via the autoglobal arrays mentioned
       above.  Older scripts, books, and tutorials may rely on this 
       directive being on.  If on, for example, one could use 
       <varname>$id</varname> from the URL 
       <literal>http://www.example.com/foo.php?id=42</literal>.  Whether on 
       or off, <varname>$_GET['id']</varname> is available.
      </simpara>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    For more details on these changes, see the section on 
    <link linkend="language.variables.predefined">predefined variables</link>
    and links therein.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="tutorial.whatsnext">
   <title>What's next?</title>
   <para>
    With what you know now you should be able to understand most of 
    the manual and also the various example scripts available in the
    example archives. You can also find other examples on the php.net
    websites in the links section:
    <ulink url="&url.php.links;">&url.php.links;</ulink>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To view various slide presentations that show more of what PHP can do, 
    see the PHP Conference Material Sites: <ulink url="&url.php.conf;">
    &url.php.conf;</ulink> and <ulink url="&url.php.talks;">&url.php.talks;
    </ulink>
   </para>
  </sect1>
 </chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"../../manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->

