<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->
<sect1 xml:id="install.windows.installer.msi" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <title>Windows Installer (PHP 5.2 and later)</title>
    <para>
     The Windows PHP installer for later versions of PHP is built using MSI
     technology using the Wix Toolkit (<link xlink:href="&url.wix;">&url.wix;</link>). 
     It will install and configure PHP and all the built-in and 
     <acronym>PECL</acronym> extensions, as well as configure many of the 
     popular web servers such as <acronym>IIS</acronym>, Apache, and Xitami.
    </para>
    
    <simpara>
     First, install your selected <acronym>HTTP</acronym> (web) server on your 
     system, and make sure that it works. Then proceed with one of the following
     install types.
    </simpara>
    
    <sect2 xml:id="install.windows.installer.msi.normal">
    <title>Normal Install</title>
     <para>
      Run the MSI installer and follow the instructions provided by the
      installation wizard. You will be prompted to select the Web Server you
      wish to configure first, along with any configuration details needed.
     </para>
     
     <para>
      You will then be prompted to select which features and extensions you
      wish to install and enable. By selecting "Will be installed on local 
      hard drive" in the drop-down menu for each item you can trigger whether
      to install the feature or not. By selecting "Entire feature will be 
      installed on local hard drive", you will be able to install all 
      sub-features of the included feature (for example by selecting this 
      option for the feature "PDO" you will install all PDO Drivers).
     </para>
     
     <warning>
      <para>
       It is not recommended to install all extensions by default, since many
       of them require dependencies from outside PHP in order to function
       properly. Instead, use the Installation Repair Mode that can be
       triggered through the 'Add/Remove Programs' control panel to
       enable or disable extensions and features after installation.
      </para>
     </warning>
     
     <para>
      The installer then sets up PHP to be used in Windows and the &php.ini;
      file, and configures certain web servers to use PHP. The installer will
      currently configure IIS, Apache, Xitami, and Sambar
      Server; if you are using a different web server you'll need to
      configure it manually. 
     </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 xml:id="install.windows.installer.msi.silent">
    <title>Silent Install</title>
     <para>
      The installer also supports a silent mode, which is helpful for Systems
      Administrators to deploy PHP easily. To use silent mode:
      <screen>
<![CDATA[       
msiexec.exe /i php-VERSION-win32-install.msi /q
]]>     
      </screen>
     </para>
     <para>
      You can control the install directory by passing it as a parameter to the
      install. For example, to install to e:\php:
      <screen>
<![CDATA[       
msiexec.exe /i php-VERSION-win32-install.msi /q INSTALLDIR=e:\php
]]>     
      </screen>
      You can also use the same syntax to specify the Apache Configuration
      Directory (APACHEDIR), the Sambar Server directory (SAMBARDIR), and the
      Xitami Server directory (XITAMIDIR).
     </para>
     <para>
      You can also specify what features to install. For example, to install 
      the mysqli extension and the CGI executable:
      <screen>
<![CDATA[       
msiexec.exe /i php-VERSION-win32-install.msi /q ADDLOCAL=cgi,ext_php_mysqli
]]>     
      </screen>
     </para>
     <para>
      The current list of Features to install is as follows:
      <screen>
<![CDATA[ 
MainExecutable - php.exe executable ( no longer available as of PHP 5.2.10/5.3.0; it is now included by default )
ScriptExecutable - php-win.exe executable
ext_php_* - the various extensions ( for example: ext_php_mysql for MySQL )
apache13 - Apache 1.3 module
apache20 - Apache 2.0 module
apache22 - Apache 2.2 module
apacheCGI - Apache CGI executable
iis4ISAPI - IIS ISAPI module
iis4CGI - IIS CGI executable
iis4FastCGI - IIS CGI executable
NSAPI - Sun/iPlanet/Netscape server module
netserve - NetServe Web Server CGI executable
Xitami - Xitami CGI executable
Sambar - Sambar Server ISAPI module
CGI - php-cgi.exe executable
PEAR - PEAR installer
Manual - PHP Manual in CHM Format
]]>
      </screen>
     </para>
     <para>
      For more information on installing MSI installers from the command line,
      visit <link xlink:href="&url.msicommandline;">&url.msicommandline;</link>
     </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 xml:id="install.windows.installer.msi.upgrade">
    <title>Upgrading PHP with the Install</title>
    
     <para>
      To upgrade, run the installer either graphically or from the command line 
      as normal. The installer will read your current install options, remove
      your old installation, and reinstall PHP with the same options as before.
      It is recommended that you use this method of keeping PHP updated instead
      of manually replacing the files in the installation directory.
     </para>
    </sect2>
    
</sect1>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
