<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->
   <sect1 xml:id="install.windows.installer" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Windows Installer (PHP 5.1.0 and earlier)</title>
    
    <para>
     The Windows PHP installer is available from the downloads page at
     <link xlink:href="&url.php.downloads;">&url.php.downloads;</link>. This
     installs the <emphasis>CGI version</emphasis> of PHP and for IIS, PWS,
     and Xitami, it configures the web server as well.  The installer does not 
     include any extra external PHP extensions (php_*.dll) as you'll only find 
     those in the Windows Zip Package and <acronym>PECL</acronym> downloads.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      While the Windows installer is an easy way to make PHP work, it is 
      restricted in many aspects as, for example, the automatic setup of 
      extensions is not supported.  Use of the installer isn't the preferred 
      method for installing PHP.
     </para>
    </note>
    
    <simpara>
     First, install your selected <acronym>HTTP</acronym> (web) server on your 
     system, and make sure that it works.
    </simpara>
    
    <simpara>
     Run the executable installer and follow the instructions provided by the
     installation wizard. Two types of installation are supported - standard,
     which provides sensible defaults for all the settings it can, and advanced,
     which asks questions as it goes along.
    </simpara>
    
    <simpara>
     The installation wizard gathers enough information to set up the &php.ini;
     file, and configure certain web servers to use PHP. One of the web servers
     the PHP installer does not configure for is Apache, so you'll need to
     configure it manually.
    </simpara>

    <simpara>
     Once the installation has completed, the installer will inform you if you
     need to restart your system, restart the server, or just start using PHP.
    </simpara>
    
    <warning>
     <para>
      Be aware, that this setup of PHP is not secure. If you would like to have
      a secure PHP setup, you'd better go on the manual way, and set every
      option carefully. This automatically working setup gives you an instantly
      working PHP installation, but it is not meant to be used on online servers.
     </para>
    </warning>
   </sect1>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
