<section id="pdo.installation">
 &reftitle.install;
 <procedure id='pdo.install.unix51up'>
  <title>PHP 5.1 and up on Unix systems</title>
  <step>
   <para>
    If you're running a PHP 5.1 release, PDO is included in the distribution;
    it will be automatically enabled when you run configure.  It is
    recommended that you build PDO as a shared extension, as this will allow
    you to take advantage of updates that are made available via PECL.  The
    recommended configure line for building PHP with PDO support should
    enable zlib support (for the pear installer) as well.  You may also need
    to enable the PDO driver for your database of choice; consult the
    documentation for  <link linkend="pdo.drivers">database-specific
    PDO drivers</link> to find out more about that, but note that if you
    build PDO as a shared extension, you must build the PDO drivers as
    shared extensions.
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
./configure --with-zlib --enable-pdo=shared --with-pdo-sqlite=shared --with-sqlite=shared
]]>
    </screen>
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    After installing PDO as a shared module, you must edit your php.ini file
    so that the PDO extension will be loaded automatically when PHP runs.
    You will also need to enable any database specific drivers there too;
    make sure that they are listed after the pdo.so line, as PDO must be
    initialized before the database-specific extensions can be loaded.
    If you built PDO and the database-specific extensions statically, you
    can skip this step.
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
extension=pdo.so
extension=pdo_sqlite.so
extension=sqlite.so
]]>
    </screen>
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Having PDO as a shared module will allow you to run <command>pear
    upgrade pdo</command> as new versions of PDO are published, without
    forcing you to rebuild the whole of PHP.  Note that if you do this, you
    also need to upgrade your database specific PDO drivers at the same
    time.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 <procedure id='pdo.install.pecl'>
  <title>PHP 5.0 and up on Unix systems</title>
  <step>
   <para>
    PDO is available as a PECL extension from
    <ulink url='&url.pecl.package;pdo'>&url.pecl.package;pdo</ulink>.
    Installation can be performed via the <command>pear</command> tool; this
    is enabled by default when you configure PHP.  You should ensure that
    PHP was configured --with-zlib in order for
    <command>pear</command> to be able to handle the compressed package
    files.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Run the following command to download, build, and install the
    latest stable version of PDO:
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
pear install pdo
]]>
    </screen>
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    The <command>pear</command> command automatically installs the
    PDO module into your PHP extensions directory. To enable the
    PDO extension on Linux or Unix operating systems, you must add
    the following line to &php.ini;:
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
extension=pdo.so
]]>
    </screen>
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information about building PECL packages, consult the
    <link linkend="install.pecl">PECL installation</link> section of the manual.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 <procedure id='pdo.install.win32php51'>
  <title>Windows users running PHP 5.1 and up</title>
  <step>
   <para>
    PDO and all the major drivers ship with PHP as shared extensions, and
    simply need to be activated by editing the &php.ini; file:
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
extension=php_pdo.dll
]]>
    </screen>
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Next, choose the other database-specific DLL files and either use 
    <function>dl</function> to load them at runtime, or enable them in
    &php.ini; below <filename>php_pdo.dll</filename>. For example:
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
extension=php_pdo.dll
extension=php_pdo_firebird.dll
extension=php_pdo_informix.dll
extension=php_pdo_mssql.dll
extension=php_pdo_mysql.dll
extension=php_pdo_oci.dll
extension=php_pdo_oci8.dll
extension=php_pdo_odbc.dll
extension=php_pdo_pgsql.dll
extension=php_pdo_sqlite.dll  
]]>
    </screen>
   </para>
   <para>
    These DLLs should exist in the system's 
    <link linkend="ini.extension-dir">extension_dir</link>.
    Note that <link linkend="ref.pdo-informix">PDO_INFORMIX</link>
    is only available as a PECL extension.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</section>
