<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->

  <chapter xml:id="install.problems" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <title>Problems?</title>

   <sect1 xml:id="install.problems.faq">
    <title>Read the FAQ</title>
    <simpara>
     Some problems are more common than others. The most
     common ones are listed in the <link linkend="faq">PHP
     FAQ</link>, part of this manual.
    </simpara>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 xml:id="install.problems.support">
    <title>Other problems</title>

    <simpara>
     If you are still stuck, someone on the PHP installation mailing list may be
     able to help you. You should check out the archive first, in case
     someone already answered someone else who had the same problem as
     you. The archives are available from the support page on <link
      xlink:href="&url.php.support;">&url.php.support;</link>. To subscribe to the PHP installation
     mailing list, send an empty mail to <link
     xlink:href="mailto:&email.php.install.subscribe;">&email.php.install.subscribe;</link>.
     The mailing list address is <link
     xlink:href="mailto:&email.php.install;">&email.php.install;</link>.
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
     If you want to get help on the mailing list, please try to be
     precise and give the necessary details about your environment
     (which operating system, what PHP version, what web server, if
     you are running PHP as CGI or a server module, &safemode;, etc.), and
     preferably enough code to make others able to reproduce and test
     your problem.
    </simpara>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 xml:id="install.problems.bugs">
    <title>Bug reports</title>
    <simpara>
     If you think you have found a bug in PHP, please report it.  The
     PHP developers probably don't know about it, and unless you
     report it, chances are it won't be fixed. You can report bugs
     using the bug-tracking system at <link
     xlink:href="&url.php.bugs;">&url.php.bugs;</link>. Please do not
     send bug reports in mailing list or personal letters. The
     bug system is also suitable to submit feature requests.
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
     Read the <link 
     xlink:href="&url.php.bugs.howtoreport;">How to report a bug</link> 
     document before submitting any bug reports!
    </simpara>
   </sect1>
  </chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
