<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->

<appendix xml:id="about" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>About the manual</title>

 <sect1 xml:id="about.formats">
  <title>Formats</title>
  <para>
   The PHP manual is provided in several formats. These formats can be divided
   into two groups: online readable formats, and downloadable packages.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    Some publishers have made available printed versions of this manual. We
    cannot recommend any of those, as they tend to become out-of-date very
    quickly.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   The manual can be read online at the <link xlink:href="&url.php;">PHP.net website</link>,
   and on the numerous mirror sites. For best performance, choose
   the closest mirror. The online version of the PHP manual has currently two
   <acronym>CSS</acronym> stylesheets, web friendly and a printer-friendly stylesheet.
  </para>
  <para>
   Two notable advantages of the online manual over most of the offline formats is the
   integration of <link linkend="about.notes">user-contributed
   notes</link> and the <link xlink:href="&url.php.urlhowto;">URL shortcuts</link> that
   may be used to get to the desired manual parts quickly. An obvious disadvantage is
   the requirement to be online to view this edition of the manual.
  </para>
  <para>
   There are several offline formats of the manual, and the most appropriate
   format for depends on the operating system, and personal
   reading style. For information on how the manual is generated in so many
   formats, read the <link linkend="about.generate">'How we generate the
   formats'</link> section of this appendix.
  </para>
  <para>
   The most cross-platform format of the manual is the HTML version. This
   is provided both as a single HTML file and as a package of individual files
   for each section (which results in a collection of several thousand files).
   We provide these versions compressed, so a decompression utility is 
   required to retrieve the files contained within the archives.
  </para>
  <!--
   The PDF version of the PHP Manual is "currently" unavailable. Perhaps
   one day it will exist.
  <para>
   Another popular cross-platform format, and the format most suited to
   printing, is PDF (also known as Adobe Acrobat). But beware that the manual
   is over 2000 pages in length, and constantly being revised.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    Many programs exist to view <acronym>PDF</acronym> files, such as the
    <link xlink:href="&url.adobe.acrobat;">Adobe Acrobat Reader</link>.
   </para>
  </note>
  -->
  <para>
   For Windows platforms, the <productname>Windows HTML Help</productname> 
   version of the manual enhances the HTML format for use with the 
   <productname>Windows HTML Help</productname> application. This
   version provides full-text search, a full index, and bookmarking. Many
   popular Windows PHP development environments also integrate with this
   version of the documentation to provide easy access. CHM viewers for
   Linux desktops are also available. Check out
   <link xlink:href="&url.xchm;">xCHM</link> or
   <link xlink:href="&url.gnochm;">GnoCHM</link>.
  </para>
  
  <para>
   There is also an <link xlink:href="&url.php.echm;">extended CHM version</link>
   available, which is updated less frequently, but provides many additional
   features. It will only work on <productname>Microsoft Windows</productname>
   though, because of the technologies used to build the help pages.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 xml:id="about.notes">
  <title>About user notes</title>
  <para>
   The user-contributed notes play an important role in the development of
   this manual. By allowing readers of the manual to contribute examples,
   caveats, and further clarifications from their browser, we are able to
   incorporate that feedback into the main text of the manual. And until the
   notes have been incorporated, they may be viewed in their submitted form
   online, and in some of the offline formats.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    The user-contributed notes are not moderated before they appear online, so
    the quality of the writing or code examples, and even the veracity of the
    contribution, cannot be guaranteed. (Not that there is any guarantee of
    the quality or accuracy of the manual text itself.)
   </para>
  </note>
  <note>
   <para>
    For the purposes of license coverage the user-contributed notes are
    considered part of the PHP manual, and are therefore covered by the
    same license that covers this documentation (Creative Commons Attribution
    at the moment). For
    more details see the <link linkend="copyright">Manual's Copyright</link>
    page.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="about.prototypes">
   <title>How to read a function definition (prototype)</title>
   <para>
    Each function in the manual is documented for quick reference. Knowing how 
    to read and understand the text will make learning PHP 
    much easier.  Rather than relying on examples or cut/paste, everyone should 
    know how to read function definitions (prototypes).  Let's begin:
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>
     Prerequisite: Basic understanding of <link linkend="language.types">types</link>
    </title>
    <para>
     Although PHP is a loosely typed language, it's important to have 
     a basic understanding of <link linkend="language.types">types</link> as 
     they have important meaning.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Function definitions tell us what 
    type of value is <link linkend="functions.returning-values">returned</link>.
    Let's use the definition for <function>strlen</function> as our first example:
   </para>
   <para>
    <screen role="html">
<![CDATA[
strlen

(PHP 4, PHP 5)
strlen -- Get string length

Description
int strlen ( string $string )

Returns the length of given string.
]]>
    </screen>
   </para>
   <para>
    <table>
     <title>Explanation of a function definition</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
       <thead>
        <row>
         <entry>Part</entry>
         <entry>Description</entry>
        </row>
       </thead>
       <tbody>
        <row>
         <entry>
          strlen
         </entry>
         <entry>
          The function name.
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          (PHP 4, PHP 5, PHP 6)
         </entry>
         <entry>
          strlen() has been around in all versions of PHP 4, PHP 5 and PHP 6
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          int
         </entry>
         <entry>
          Type of value this function returns, which is an 
          <type>integer</type> (i.e. the length of a string is measured in
          numbers). 
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          ( string $string )
         </entry>
         <entry>
          The first (and in this case the only) parameter/argument for this 
          function is named <parameter>string</parameter>, and it's a 
          <type>string</type>.
         </entry>
        </row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
     </table>
    </para>
    <para>
     We could rewrite the above function definition in a generic way:
    </para>
    <para>
     <screen>
<![CDATA[
      returned type    function name    ( parameter type   parameter name )
]]>
     </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
     Many functions take on multiple parameters, such as <function>in_array</function>.
     Its prototype is as follows:
    </para>
    <para>
     <screen>    
<![CDATA[
      bool in_array ( mixed $needle, array $haystack [, bool $strict])
]]>
     </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
     What does this mean?  in_array() returns a 
     <link linkend="language.types.boolean">boolean</link> value, &true; on 
     success (if the <parameter>needle</parameter> was found in the 
     <parameter>haystack</parameter>)&return.falseforfailure; (if the 
     <parameter>needle</parameter> was not found in the 
     <parameter>haystack</parameter>).  The first parameter is named 
     <parameter>needle</parameter> and it can be of many different 
     <link linkend="language.types">types</link>, so we call it 
     "<emphasis>mixed</emphasis>".  This mixed <parameter>needle</parameter> 
     (what we're looking for) can be either a scalar value (string, integer, 
     or <link linkend="language.types.float">float</link>), or an
     <link linkend="language.types.array">array</link>.
     <parameter>haystack</parameter> (the array we're searching in) is the 
     second parameter.  The third <emphasis>optional</emphasis> parameter is 
     named <parameter>strict</parameter>.  All optional parameters are seen 
     in <emphasis>[</emphasis> brackets <emphasis>]</emphasis>.  The manual 
     states that the <parameter>strict</parameter> parameter defaults to 
     boolean &false;.  See the manual page on each function for details on 
     how they work.
    </para>
    <para>
     There are also functions with more complex PHP version information. Take
     <function>html_entity_decode</function> as an example:
    </para>
    <para>
     <screen>    
<![CDATA[
(PHP 4 >= 4.3.0, PHP 5)
]]>
     </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
     This means that this function has only been
     available in a released version since PHP 4.3.0. 
    </para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 xml:id="about.phpversions">
  <title>PHP versions documented in this manual</title>
  <para>
   <!-- FIXME PHP_6 What is the latest? -->
   The manual contains information about past, current, and future versions
   of PHP. Changes in behaviour are documented as notes, changelogs, and 
   inline text within the manual pages. 
   The earliest documented version is PHP 4.1.0, 
   whereas the latest is PHP 5.x.x.
  </para>
  <para>
   Documentation partly exists for the SVN version of PHP, which
   always means the very latest development version. This has yet to
   be released so is only available through the SVN version handling system, 
   or via a <link xlink:href="&url.php.snapshots;">snapshot</link>. So be aware that
   features marked "available in SVN" are typically unavailable. These 
   features, though, will most likely be available in the next stable version 
   of PHP. To download the SVN version, see the <link xlink:href="&url.php.anonsvn;">anonymous
   SVN access page</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   So, documentation may exist for PHP versions that aren't yet released.
   (Something like PHP 6.x.x while the latest stable version might be 
   5.x.x). Most of the time, this is not an error in the documentation.
   Explanation is often added for features not available in the current
   PHP release, but will be available as a known future PHP version.
   Typically, PHP only adds new features in major releases otherwise only bugs
   are fixed. Using the A.B.C versioning format, a major release increments A 
   or B whereas minor releases increment C. So for example it's not uncommon 
   for a feature to be documented as available in PHP x.1.x when the latest 
   release is PHP x.0.x. Also note that the manual is written in present 
   tense, not future tense.
  </para>
  <para>
   Many times the PHP manual lists "Default Values" for PHP directives. These 
   values are based on <filename>php.ini-development</filename> and not 
   <filename>php.ini-production</filename>. They also refer to the latest  
   version of PHP. See the <link linkend="ini.list">PHP directive 
   appendix</link> for details on these values and changes.
  </para>
 </sect1>
   
 <sect1 xml:id="about.more">
  <title>How to find more information about PHP</title>
  <para>
   This manual does not attempt to provide instruction about general
   programming practices. First-time - or even just beginning -
   programmers may find it difficult to learn how to program in PHP using
   this manual exclusively. Instead, seek out a text more oriented towards
   beginners.
  </para>
  <para>
   There are a number of active mailing lists for discussion on all aspects of
   programming with PHP. If stuck with a problem, consider using these lists.
   For support options, including mailing lists, view <link
   xlink:href="&url.php.support;">the PHP.net support page</link>. Furthermore, 
   there is a list of websites devoted to PHP articles, forums, and code galleries
   at <link xlink:href="&url.php.links;">the PHP.net links page</link>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="about.howtohelp">
  <title>How to help improve the documentation</title>
  <para>
   There are three ways everyone can help improve this documentation.
  </para>
  <para>
   If an error is found in this manual, in any language, please report them
   using the bug system at <link xlink:href="&url.php.bugs;">&url.php.bugs;</link>.
   Classify the bug as <literal>"Documentation Problem"</literal>. All documentation related
   problems, including those about manual formats, should be submitted as bug 
   reports.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    Please don't abuse the bug system by submitting requests for help. 
    Instead, use one of the many 
    <link xlink:href="&url.php.support;">support options</link>.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   By contributing notes, users may provide additional examples, caveats, and
   clarifications for other readers. But please do not submit bug reports using the
   annotation system. For details, see the section titled <link
   linkend="about.notes">'About user notes'</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The PHP manual is translated into many languages. Knowing English and a
   foreign language allows for another way to help improve the PHP manual by
   working with a translation team. For information about starting a new 
   translation, or helping a currently translated version, please read
   <link xlink:href="&url.php.dochowto;">&url.php.dochowto;</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The PHP Documentation Project also has an IRC channel where many manual
   authors hang out. Stop by <literal>#php.doc</literal> on
   <literal>irc.efnet.org</literal> and discuss ways to improve
   the PHP documentation.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 xml:id="about.generate">
  <title>How we generate the formats</title>
  <para>
   This manual is written in <acronym>XML</acronym> using the <link
   xlink:href="&url.docbook.xml;">DocBook XML DTD</link>, using <link
   xlink:href="&url.phd;"><acronym>PhD</acronym></link> (The [PH]P based 
   [D]ocBook renderer) for maintenance and formatting.
  </para>
  <para>
   Using <acronym>XML</acronym> as a source format gives 
   the ability to generate many output formats from the source
   files, while only maintaining one source document for all formats.
   The tool used for formatting the online manual is <link
   xlink:href="&url.phd;">PhD</link>.
   We use <link xlink:href="&url.winhelp;">Microsoft HTML Help
   Workshop</link> to generate the <productname>Windows HTML Help</productname> format
   of the manual, and of course PHP itself to do some
   additional conversions and formatting.
  </para>
  <para>
   The PHP manual is generated in various languages and formats, see 
   <link xlink:href="&url.php.docs;">&url.php.docs;</link> for additional details.
   The <acronym>XML</acronym> source code may be downloaded from SVN and
   viewed at <link xlink:href="&url.php.svn;">&url.php.svn;</link>. The
   documentation is stored in the <literal>phpdoc</literal> module.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="about.translations">
  <title>Translations</title>
  <para>
   The PHP manual is available not only in various formats, but
   also in various languages. The text of the 
   manual is first written in English, then teams of people across 
   the world take care of translating it to their native languages.
   If a translation for a specified function or chapter has not yet
   been made, the manual's build system falls back to the 
   English version of it.
  </para>
  <para>
   People involved in the translations start from the <acronym>XML</acronym>
   source code available from <link xlink:href="&url.php.svn;">&url.php.svn;</link>
   and from it they translate to their mother language. They do 
   <emphasis>not use</emphasis> the generated versions (like 
   <acronym>HTML</acronym> or plain text) as it's the build system that takes 
   care of the conversions from <acronym>XML</acronym> to human readable 
   formats.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    To help translate the documentation, 
    please get in touch with the translation/documentation team by
    subscribing to the phpdoc mailing list: send an empty mail to <link
    xlink:href="mailto:&email.php.doc.subscribe;">&email.php.doc.subscribe;</link>.
    The mailing list address is <literal>&email.php.doc;</literal>. State in the
    message an interest in translating the manual and someone will reply with
    feedback on moving forward by helping start a new language translation, or 
    by contacting the existing team for the desired language.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   At the moment the manual is available, partly or not, in over 10 languages.
  </para>
  <para>
   They may all be downloaded here: <link xlink:href="&url.php.docs;">&url.php.docs;</link>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

</appendix>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
