<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.19 $ -->

<!--
  TODO: add manual conventions section (eg. how to read
        function usage parts, what is fixed width, what is
        bold, what is linked
        
        add some tips about combining the versions (online-
        offline), and using "http://anymirror.php.net/funcname"
-->
<appendix id="about">
 <title>About the manual</title>

 <sect1 id="about.formats">
  <title>Formats</title>
  <para>
   The PHP manual is provided in several formats. These formats can be divided
   into two groups: online readable formats, and downloadable packages.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    Some publishers have made available printed versions of this manual. We
    cannot recommend any of those, as they tend to become out-of-date very
    quickly.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   You can read the manual online at <ulink url="&url.php;">&url.php;</ulink>
   and on the numerous mirror sites. For best performance, you should choose
   the mirror site closest to you. You can view the manual in either its plain
   (print-friendly) HTML format or an HTML format that integrates the manual
   into the look and feel of the PHP website itself.
  </para>
  <para>
   An advantage of the online manual over most of the offline formats is the
   integration of <link linkend="about.notes">user-contributed
   notes</link>. An obvious disadvantage is that you have to be online to view
   the manual in the online formats.
  </para>
  <para>
   There are several offline formats of the manual, and the most appropriate
   format for you depends on what operating system you use and your personal
   reading style. For information on how the manual is generated in so many
   formats, read the <link linkend="about.generate">'How we generate the
   formats'</link> section of this appendix.
  </para>
  <para>
   The most cross-platform formats of the manual are the HTML and plain-text
   versions. The HTML format is provided both as a single HTML file and as
   a package of individual files for each section (which results in a
   collection of several thousand files). The HTML and plaintext formats are
   provided as tar files compressed using the bzip2 archiver.
  </para>
  <para>
   Another popular cross-platform format, and the format most suited to
   printing, is PDF (also known as Adobe Acrobat). But before you rush to
   download this format and hit the Print button, be warned that the manual is
   nearly 2000 pages long, and constantly being revised.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    If you do not already have a program capable of viewing PDF format
    files, you may need to download <ulink url="&url.adobe.acrobat;">Adobe
    Acrobat Reader</ulink>.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   For owners of Palm-compatible handhelds, the Palm document and iSilo
   formats are ideal for this platform. You can bring your handheld with you
   on your daily commute and use a <ulink url="&url.palm.doc;">DOC</ulink>
   or <ulink url="&url.palm.isilo;">iSilo</ulink> reader to brush up on your
   PHP knowledge, or just use it as a quick reference.
  </para>
  <para>
   For Windows platforms, the Windows HTML Help version of the manual soups up
   the HTML format for use with the Windows HTML Help application. This
   version provides full-text search, a full index, and bookmarking. Many
   popular Windows PHP development environments also integrate with this
   version of the documentation to provide easy access.
  </para>
<!--
  mmmm, this project seems to be dead. Any news?
  <note>
   <para>
    A Visual Basic for Linux project is in the planning stage, which will
    include the development of a CHM Creator and Viewer for Linux. See their
    <ulink url="&url.vb4linux;">SourceForge.net page</ulink> if you are
    interested in the progress.
   </para>
  </note>
  -->
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="about.notes">
  <title>About user notes</title>
  <para>
   The user-contributed notes play an important role in the development of
   this manual. By allowing readers of the manual to contribute examples,
   caveats, and further clarifications from their browser, we are able to
   incorporate that feedback into the main text of the manual. And until the
   notes have been incorporated, they can be viewed in their submitted form
   online and in some of the offline formats.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    The user-contributed notes are not moderated before they appear online, so
    the quality of the writing or code examples, and even the veracity of the
    contribution, cannot be guaranteed. (Not that there is any guarantee of
    the quality or accuracy of the manual text itself.)
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="about.prototypes">
   <title>How to read a function definition (prototype)</title>
   <para>
    Each function is documented for quick reference, knowing how 
    to read and understand the manual will make using PHP 
    much easier.  Rather than relying on examples or cut/paste, you want 
    to know how to read function definitions (prototypes).  Let's begin:
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>
     Prerequisite: Basic understanding of <link linkend="language.types">types</link>
    </title>
    <para>
     Although PHP is a loosly typed language, it's important to have 
     a basic understanding of <link linkend="language.types">types</link> as 
     they have important meaning.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Function definitions tell us what 
    type of value is <link linkend="functions.returning-values">returned</link>, 
    let's use the definition for <function>strlen</function> as our first example:
   </para>
   <para>
    <screen role="html">
strlen

(PHP 3, PHP 4 >= 4.0.0)
strlen -- Get string length

Description
int strlen ( string str )

Returns the length of string.
    </screen>
   </para>
   <para>
    <table>
     <title>Explanation of a function definition</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
       <thead>
        <row>
         <entry>Part</entry>
         <entry>Description</entry>
        </row>
       </thead>
       <tbody>
        <row>
         <entry>
          strlen
         </entry>
         <entry>
          The function name.
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          (PHP 3, PHP 4 >= 4.0.0)
         </entry>
         <entry>
          strlen() has been around in both all of PHP 3 and PHP 4
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          int
         </entry>
         <entry>
          Type of value this function returns, which is an 
          <link linkend="language.types.integer">integer</link>
          (i.e. The length of a string is measured in numbers).
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          ( string str )
         </entry>
         <entry>
          The first (and in this case the only) parameter/argument for the 
          function strlen() is named <parameter>str</parameter>, and it's a 
          <link linkend="language.types.string">string</link>.
         </entry>
        </row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
     </table>
    </para>
    <para>
     We could rewrite the above function definition in a generic way:
    </para>
    <para>
     <screen role="html">
      returned type    function name    ( parameter type   parameter name )
     </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
     Many functions take on multiple parameters, such as <function>in_array</function>.
     It's prototype is as follows:
    </para>
    <para>
     <screen role="html">    
      bool in_array ( mixed needle, array haystack [, bool strict])
     </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
     What does this mean?  in_array() returns a 
     <link linkend="language.types.boolean">boolean</link> value, &true; on 
     success (the <parameter>needle</parameter> was found in the 
     <parameter>haystack</parameter>) or &false; on failure (the 
     <parameter>needle</parameter> was not found in the 
     <parameter>haystack</parameter>).  The first parameter is named 
     <parameter>needle</parameter> and it can be many different 
     <link linkend="language.types">types</link>, so we call it 
     "<emphasis>mixed</emphasis>".  This mixed <parameter>needle</parameter> 
     (what we're looking for) can either be a scalar value (string, integer, 
     or <link linkend="language.types.float">float</link>), or an
     <link linkend="language.types.array">array</link>.  
     <parameter>haystack</parameter> (the array we're searching in) is the 
     second parameter.  The third <emphasis>optional</emphasis> parameter is 
     named <parameter>strict</parameter>.  All optional parameters are seen 
     in <emphasis>[</emphasis> brackets <emphasis>]</emphasis>.  The manual 
     states that the <parameter>strict</parameter> parameter defaults to 
     boolean &false;.  See the manual page on each function for details on 
     how they work.
    </para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="about.phpversions">
  <title>PHP versions documented in this manual</title>
  <para>
   This documentation contains information about PHP 4, with some added
   migration and compatibility notes regarding PHP 3. Behaviour,
   parameter, return value and other changes between different PHP
   versions are documented in notes and inline text in the manual.
  </para>
  <para>
   You may find documentation pieces for the CVS version of PHP, which
   always means the very latest development version available through
   the CVS version handling system. If you are not a developer of PHP
   itself, and you are not keen on using the very latest development
   version of PHP, features marked with the "available in CVS" wording
   are not accessible to you. Though these features will probably be
   available in the next stable version of PHP. If you would like to
   download the CVS version, see the <ulink url="&url.php.anoncvs;">anonymous
   CVS access page</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
   You may also encounter documentation for a PHP version which is
   not released (something like PHP 4.3.0 as the latest stable version
   is 4.2.3). Most of the time, this is not an error in the documentation.
   Explanation is often added for features not available in the current
   PHP release, but will be available in a known future PHP version.
  </para>
 </sect1>
   
 <sect1 id="about.more">
  <title>How to find more information about PHP</title>
  <para>
   This manual does not attempt to provide instruction about general
   programming practices. If you are a first-time, or even just a beginning,
   programmer, you may find it difficult to learn how to program in PHP using
   just this manual. You may want to seek out a text more oriented towards
   beginners. You can find a list of PHP-related books at <ulink
   url="&url.php.books;">&url.php.books;</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
   There are a number of active mailing lists for discussion of all aspects of
   programming with PHP. If you find yourself stuck on a problem for which you
   can't find your own solution, you may be able to get help from someone on
   these lists. You can find a list of the mailing lists at <ulink
   url="&url.php.support;">&url.php.support;</ulink>, as well as links to the
   mailing list archives and other online support resources. Furthermore, at
   <ulink url="&url.php.links;">&url.php.links;</ulink> there is a list of
   websites devoted to PHP articles, forums, and code galleries.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="about.howtohelp">
  <title>How to help improve the documentation</title>
  <para>
   There are three ways you can help to improve this documentation.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you find errors in this manual, in any language, please report them
   using the bug system at <ulink url="&url.php.bugs;">&url.php.bugs;</ulink>.
   Classify the bug as "Documentation Problem". You can also submit problems
   related to specific manual formats here.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    Please don't abuse the bug system by submitting requests for help. Use the
    mailing lists or community sites mentioned earlier, instead.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   By contributing notes, you can provide additional examples, caveats, and
   clarifications for other readers. But do not submit bug reports using the
   annotation system please. You can read more about annotations in the <link
   linkend="about.notes">'About user notes'</link> section of this
   appendix.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you know English and some foreign language, you may also
   help out in the translations. If you would like to start a new
   translation, or help in a translation project, please read
   <ulink url="&url.php.dochowto;">&url.php.dochowto;</ulink>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="about.generate">
  <title>How we generate the formats</title>
  <para>
   This manual is written in <acronym>XML</acronym> using the <ulink
   url="&url.docbook.xml;">DocBook XML DTD</ulink>, using <ulink
   url="&url.dsssl;"><acronym>DSSSL</acronym></ulink> (Document
   Style and Semantics Specification Language) for formatting, and
   experimentally the <ulink url="&url.xslt;"><acronym>XSLT</acronym>
   </ulink> (Extensible Stylesheet Language Transformations)
   for maintenance and formatting.
  </para>
  <para>
   Using <acronym>XML</acronym> as a source format gives us
   the ability to generate many output formats from the source
   files, while only maintaining one source document for all formats.
   The tools used for formatting <acronym>HTML</acronym> and
   <acronym>TeX</acronym> versions are
   <ulink url="&url.jade;">Jade</ulink>, written by <ulink
   url="&url.jclark;">James Clark</ulink> and <ulink
   url="&url.dbstyle;">The Modular DocBook Stylesheets</ulink>
   written by <ulink url="&url.nwalsh;">Norman Walsh</ulink>.
   We use <ulink url="&url.winhelp;">Microsoft HTML Help
   Workshop</ulink> to generate the Windows HTML Help format
   of the manual, and of course PHP itself to do some
   additional conversions and formatting.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can download the manual in various languages and
   formats, including plain text, plain <acronym>HTML</acronym>,
   <acronym>PDF</acronym>, PalmPilot DOC, PalmPilot iSilo and
   Windows HTML Help, from
   <ulink url="&url.php.docs;">&url.php.docs;</ulink>.
   The manuals are updated automatically as the text is updated.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can find more information about downloading the
   <acronym>XML</acronym> source code of this documentation
   at <ulink url="&url.php.cvs;">&url.php.cvs;</ulink>. The
   documentation is stored in the <literal>phpdoc</literal> module.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="about.translations">
  <title>Translations</title>
  <para>
   The PHP manual is not only available in various formats,
   it is also available in various languages. The text of the 
   manual is first written in english, then teams of people across 
   the world take care of translating it to their native language.
   If a translation for a specified function or chapter has not yet
   been made, the build system of the manual falls back to the 
   english version of it.
  </para>
  <para>
   Peoples involved in the translations start from the <acronym>XML</acronym>
   source code available from <ulink url="&url.php.cvs;">&url.php.cvs;</ulink>
   and from it they translate to thier mother language. They do 
   <emphasis>not use</emphasis> the <acronym>HTML</acronym>, the plain text, 
   or the <acronym>PDF</acronym> version. It is the build system which takes 
   care of the conversions from <acronym>XML</acronym> to human readable formats.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    If you would like to help translating the documentation to your native 
    language, please get in touch with the translation/documentation team
    subscribing to the phpdoc mailinglist: send an empty mail to <ulink
    url="mailto:&email.php.doc.subscribe;">&email.php.doc.subscribe;</ulink>.
    The mailing list address is <literal>&email.php.doc;</literal>. State in the
    message that you are interested in translating the manual to a language 
    and someone will get back to you, helping you start a new language translation 
    or reach the already active documentation team for your language.
   </para>    
  </note>
  <para>
   At the moment the manual is available, partly or not, in the following languages:
   Brazilian Portuguese, Chinese, Czech, Dutch, French, German, Hungarian, Italian, 
   Japanese, Korean, Polish and Spanish.
  </para>
  <para>
   They all can be downloaded here: <ulink url="&url.php.docs;">&url.php.docs;</ulink>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

</appendix>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"../../manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
