<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->
<book xml:id="book.hash" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <?phpdoc extension-membership="core" ?>
 <title>HASH Message Digest Framework</title>
 <titleabbrev>Hash</titleabbrev>
 
 <!-- {{{ preface -->
 <preface xml:id="intro.hash">
  &reftitle.intro;
  <para>
   This extension provides functions that can be used for direct or
   incremental processing of arbitrary length messages using a variety of
   hashing algorithms, including the generation of <acronym>HMAC</acronym>
   values and key derivations including <acronym>HKDF</acronym> and
   <acronym>PBKDF2</acronym>.
  </para>
  <para>
   There are roughly three categories of hashing algorithms, and a complete list of
   algorithms can be found in the documentation for <function>hash_algos</function>.

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
      Checksum algorithms (such as <literal>"crc32b"</literal> or <literal>"adler32"</literal>):
      These are used to calculate checksums, useful in situations such as when
      transmission errors are to be detected. They are often very fast. These
      algorithms often generate values that are easily "guessable" or can be manipulated
      to create collisions, so they are entirely unsuitable for cryptographic use.
     </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
      Non-cryptographic algorithms (such as the xxHash family):
      These are often used to calculate hash values for hash tables, as they are
      designed to yield a good distribution over arbitrary string inputs. They
      are also generally fast, but also not suitable for cryptographic use.
     </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
      Cryptographic algorithms (such as the SHA-2 family):
      These are designed to yield hash values that are representative of their
      inputs but are not guessable nor prone to collisions. Performance is often
      a secondary concern, but modern hardware often supports special handling
      for these algorithms that PHP tries to use when available.
     </simpara>
     <simpara>
      The Computer Security Resource Center of the <acronym>NIST</acronym> has
      <link xlink:href="&url.hash.nist-hash-functions;">explanation of the algorithms
      currently approved by United States Federal Information Processing
      Standards</link>.
     </simpara>
     <caution>
      <para>
       Some of the early cryptographic algorithms, such as <literal>"md4"</literal>,
       <literal>"md5"</literal>, and <literal>"sha1"</literal>, have been proven
       to be prone to collision attacks and it is generally recommended to no
       longer use these for cryptographic applications.
      </para>
     </caution>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
   See also the <link linkend="faq.passwords">FAQ on Safe Password Hashing</link>
   for information on best practices for using hash functions in handling
   passwords.
  </para>
 </preface>
 <!-- }}} -->
 
 &reference.hash.setup;
 &reference.hash.constants;
 &reference.hash.hashcontext;
 &reference.hash.reference;

</book>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
